Okay. Thanks for,
everyone for, attending this workshop.
So this is the third workshop
on the data problems for
foundation models.
So, it's very fortunate that, we can
make the make it the third time,
at, Eyrie Reis here.
And this year, we have
168 submissions which
is more than 50% increase from
last year. And one
remark for this, the
real process is that
so we did a pretty strict transcription
check for all the submissions.
And there are actually more than 15%,
of the submissions for, having
hallucinated citations. So,
we have to, test through check that.
And, out of the, all
the submissions, we pick one best
paper, award and one,
or mention, which will be presented
by, Cornell in the morning session, and
one from Jacqueline for,
the afternoon session.
And this year, we also,
have we also sent out a bunch of the
early career registration
award, and also the, outstanding
reward. Thanks for the sponsorship
from, Snorkel AI and Italji AI.
So this year's, the organization
team is led by Yu Zheng
and Lucy, and
also and and also
me and John and Rossi,
and Martin and Monica and
Pratish.
Yeah. And this year, we got very
generous, sponsor
sponsorship from, Snorkel and,
Datology.
So Yeah. So for the morning session,
we will first have two invited talks.
And after a coffee break, we'll have three oral
presentations, and then followed by the
poster session. And the lunchbox will be
provided for
during the lunch break.
And then followed by, the afternoon session,
which we'll have a one invited
talk, followed with three oral sessions,
and then and then, and
then another, another invited talk
from Snorkel AI, followed by
the sponsor talk. Yeah.
Yeah. So there's not too much to
cover for the opening.
So let's go to the
first invited talk
by, Baharen.
You want to come here Yeah.
Yeah. So, Bahar is a assistant professor
in the computer science department
at UCLA. Who her
research aims to address sustainability,
reliability, and efficient on
improving the big data quality by
developing selectively rigorous methods
to select the most
beneficial data for efficient and robust
learning. Besides she's also interested
in improving the models and learning algorithms.
Before joining, UCLA, she was a postdoc
at Stanford and received
her PhD in, CS
department from
ETH. Should you
receive ETH medal for sending
of deceased, so was selected as a rising
star in ECI's by
MIT. And also received
a bunch of other, awards. Yeah.
So for today's talk, I shall talk about
the post training data curation. Yeah. Let's
welcome, Baharin.
Thank you so much, for the organizers.
Okay. So much for the organizers
for the workshop, and so much
for being here early morning.
Okay. So today, I want to talk about reasoning
models. And in general the
data that we need to
enable the large language models
to reason efficiently and
effectively. So I'm going to talk about some
theoretical stuff, but I'm not going to show
you too many equations. I'm just keeping it high
level details. You can check the papers.
And also some empirical results
on the empirical sites, how we can generate
high quality data for training reasoning
models. So let's
start with like, a very brief overview
Like, recently, we have observed this
which from system one
technically to system two thinking.
Where traditionally, we were asking the
large language models to answer
like, quickly whatever
question we have. Like, it usually a
question and a short answer.
We would ask the models to give us
But more recently, we are kind of making
this shift towards asking
them to think for a long time
before outputting any answer. And this
is usually very, very beneficial for more
complex and complicated type of task.
Like mathematical reasoning or scientific
type of reasoning. So
So just a quick kind
of overview just to make a distinction
between instruction tuning and
training models to reason.
So here I have listed some of the
kind of obvious
differences. As a brief overview.
So when we are training
language models for instruction tuning, we are
usually training them on
pairs of instructions and answers.
Instruction outputs. And these
are improving the model's ability to
follow in
And So we
can kind of insert the
this let's think step by step in
the prompt such that they can
think for a few steps before outputting
that short answer. Usually, this
entire sequence, this entire
prompt slash response, length of it is
usually short. It less than
1,500 characters.
But when we talk about reasoning models,
these reasoning models are pro are trained
to kind of produce very, very long steps
of thinking or chain of thoughts.
And this is to to solve very
complicated task. Usually, the entire
sequence is up to 100,000
Right? So there is a very kind
of, obvious distinctions
between the two. Although instruction tuning models can
also think, but they usually think for
a very short time. In contrast, reasoning
models usually tend to think for very, very
long time. Take their time,
slow thinking, and then output answer.
And this talk is all about the right
part. Reasoning models.
And And what is the benefit? So traditionally,
Google has spend all our
compute when we are talking about instruction
tuning or other paradigms we are spending
all the compute during the training We
try to train these language models or
other models the best way that we can.
Such that we can get the best performance
out of them. But when we talk about
reasoning models, there is a difference.
Because these models are able
to think for
a long time, and they can do this
at the test time, At test time, we can just
give them a lot of compute.
A good amount of time, that
they can take their time. They produce very
long chains of thoughts, many steps
of reasoning, and then they output the
answer. And as you can see, the left
plot shows the accuracy on the
y axis versus the
train time compute, the amount of time we spent
during training.
And, of course, if we spend more time during training,
you train this models on larger
datasets, y axis performance
improves. But the right
plot shows the same thing performance
on the y axis versus test time compute.
Right? So if we give these reasoning models
more time during test at inference
time, can just think
more and more and they can generate a
higher quality answer. So we get another
performance improvement or similar performance
improvement during the test. So
this is the difference.
And this phenomenon is called test
time escape. So we can scale the compute
at test time to further improve the performance.
So Okay. So
let's kind of brief a recap
of how we can enable LLMs
to reason.
So we have the pretraining stage,
which any language model
goes through. We are going to train
these LLMs on huge amount
of data, usually crawled from the Internet.
And this gives them basic knowledge, like linguistic
knowledge, general board on
in general knowledge about different things.
But this does not enable to the enable them
to necessarily do q one a
question answering. Right? So as to enable them to
do question answering or
reasoning, we need this additional
post training stage or fine tuning stage.
So there are two ways we can do post training.
For language models. One is supervised fine
tuning, which which shows
that if we are doing instruction tuning, it just shows
them pairs of questions and ask And if you are doing
reasoning, it shows them the
question. Very long chain of thought,
and then the answer. Right? So this is
going to be supervised fine tuning, which
supervises all the intermediate reasoning steps.
Alternate alternatively, we can do reinforcement
learning. Where we show the
model question We ask them to think
on their own. As much as
they want and come up with an answer, and we
just reward the output or
the outcome. And this is called outcome
supervision. In contrast to
process supervision, which is SFG.
And one tricky kind of,
thing here is that usually, it is very
hard evaluate the
pretrained models. Because after pretraining, we
cannot do QA. It is very hard to
measure the performance
of the pretrained models. So we can usually
measure the performance only after post
training. So it
is a little bit hard to kind of
pretraining affects the performance of post
training. But it is hard to measure
it right after pretraining. So
the quality of pretraining and the quality of
posttraining, both of them, we only measure
after post training. So it makes a little
bit makes it a little bit
complicated to measure what is
good pretraining data, what is good posttraining data
because there is an interaction and there is a synergy.
Okay. So today, I want to talk about this
particular four quest
So first of all, what
is the effect of thinking like
on SFT and RL? Like, if we do
if we train these reasoning models to think
with SFD or RL, what's the difference?
What is it that they learn differently? And what
is the effect on optimization?
What is a good SFT
or RL data? For enabling these
language models to reason?
When do we get improvement if we do
test time scaling, if we scale the
compute at test time? And when we do not get
that improvement? Right,
And finally, more
on the empirical side, how can we curate
our high quality SFT or RL
data to train these models to reason?
So the first two parts are more on the theoretical
side, but again, I it very high level. I mainly
talk about intuitions. And then eventually,
we talk about some actual methods
to curate. This resulting data to
post train parallelism to reason.
Okay. Let's start with the first part.
Just like a very quick recap
of the theoretical setting, which usually
need some simplified setting for the sake
of theoretical analysis, and then we have
apply the insight. To
real language models in practice. So
the setting here, we are considering an
in context linear regression task.
Which means that the
data the sake of training that we use,
is in the form of this matrix.
Of x and y.
So for every kind
of in context matrix that you see
here, there is a w
So here if you see my cursor, there's a
w here. And we are
kind of generating these xls
from a normal distribution, multiplying them
by this w to get the voice.
So this is a linear regression task, and we
are putting all this in context
linear regression examples. We are putting
all these examples coming from linear regression
in the context, which is this e matrix.
Now, how can we model
reasoning or chain of thought The way
that we model reasoning is shown in
the bottom. We put
all the examples in the context pairs of
x and y. Then we
add this column which includes
w zero.
And w zero is initialized by zero
initially. And then we input
this first part of the matrix to the
model, and the model is a linear self
attention. And
we ask it to come up with the next column,
which contains w one.
Then we include all this first part of
the matrix including w zero and
w one to the model. And we ask you to
output the next column, which is going to be w
two. So we can do this for
k steps, and k can be an arbitrary
number. Such that we
model long chain of thoughts
thinking for k steps. And then the
last column, which contains
w I, or WK,
this is gonna be the solution of the
model after k step of thinking, which
we like it to be similar to that original
w. That we use to generate
all the x and ys. Right? So the
model is supposed to think and
solve a linear regression task.
So this is the theoretical model.
And now we can define the loss in two ways.
First is that we can define the SFT
loss, which is the process
reward. And this is going to ask
the like, this is going to check all the w's
to be similar to the w's
if you do gradient descent to solve that
linear regression task. Right? Not transformer,
just normal gradient descent.
On linear refresh.
Right? So we can either supervise all the
steps of thinking with two model
SFT, or we can only supervise
the last final solution.
And that is kind of the outcome
supervision or closer
to the reinforcement learning parallel.
Right. So steps of thinking the way that
model thinks, the data, everything is the same.
Just changing the loss
like, either checking all the intermediate
solutions or the
final outcome are going to model SFT
or outcome supervision slash RA.
Okay. So this is the setting.
So now if we analyze this setting, if
we train this transformer linear
self attention with gradient descent,
let's first see like,
analyze SFG. Like, how would
the optimization be if we do SFT?
So to keep it
short, the solution
that we find for
this linear regression
The does not depend on how many
steps you think. And does not
depend on if you think at all or not.
Right? So thinking or not thinking does not
change the solution for a given reasoning
data that we are doing post training on or
training on.
So The solution depends on
the prompt length. Number of x and y that
we have in in context, and
the the number of them, the number of data points that
you are training the model on. Does
not depend on how many steps you think to get
that final solution.
Which is interesting. But what is the benefit
of thinking here? Is there any benefit for thinking?
And yes, the benefit is that if
you think during the
training for SFT,
you get much faster convergence.
Like, you can train your model much
much faster compared to to the
case that we do not think at all.
So in this case, there is this obvious benefit
of faster convergence. So
this this shows that the solution is only
dependent on the properties of data.
And here you are saying that if
you think more, this alpha is going to be larger,
so convergence will be much faster.
So Okay. So
this result only holds for a
given particular training data.
Coming from a linear regression task, but it
does not tell us what is a good
SFT data. It just tells me that
if I train with thinking,
with chain of thought, I'm going to find
my solution much faster. Which
is good. But it doesn't say which data
is good. Like, which data improves
the performance of my model the best.
Yes.
Sure.
Good question.
You come to the, like, the mic for, like,
can't I can't repeat the question.
The question is what is the context? What is
context length? And what is the context?
So the context is the number of eggs and
voice. Like, this is the in
context example. The full thing is one in
context example. And m
is the number of examples I
have in the context. So I can
have more pairs of x and y coming from
the same w or I can have less number of
x and y coming from the same w.
And the number of these matrices is
the number of prompts.
And the number of x and y in every
prompt is the length of the prompt or the in context
Great question. Thanks.
So here, I'm going to skip all the equations,
and I'm just going to show you the answer.
So the answer is that given a
pre trained model, this pre trained model has some
knowledge. About different tasks,
So the best SFD data
is the one that has technically no overlap
with the pretraining data.
Overlap in 10 in terms of content.
Like if you want to think of it intuitively.
If you want to think of it mathematically in terms
of the directions of the data covariance,
metrics. Right?
But technically, we want the SFT data that
has no overlap with the pretraining
data. And we
want a small set of
such examples. And what are
these examples? These are the examples that are
hard, very hard for the model to
answer. Technically. Like, for the minimum
overlap case, the less
your post training overlaps with
pretraining, post training task is
gonna be harder for the model.
Right? There if there's more overlap, this is going to
be a much easier task for the model.
So the best SFT data is the one that is
hardest for the model, and we want it
to be small.
Okay. What if we have overlap?
Interestingly, if we have a little
bit of overlap, that
makes the situation much worse
than if we have larger amount of overlap.
What I mean is if no overlap
is the optimum, is the best, But
if there is overlap, it is
even better that you have a larger overlap
compared to a smaller overlap. Because
if you have a smaller overlap, you are technically
going to forget many of the pretraining
informations and focusing on that
at a small overlap case. If
you have larger overlap, you can
increase the size of your SFD data and
you can still get some
reasonable performance. It's not going to be
as good as the first case, which is no
overlap, but it's gonna be better than the middle
case. So this plot that
you are showing here this is showing the
error, like a smaller better on the y
axis. Versus the number
of prompts number of training data points.
And left case is no overlap. And
the scale of y axis is
a little bit different. That's why
you may not see it from far away.
But the error in the left case is much lower
than the middle and right. And the
error in the middle case is much higher than the right.
And there is this double descent phenomenon.
As we increase the number of examples or the number
of prompts, error goes up and then
goes down. Okay.
So short message is that SFT should be
small and as hard as
possible for the given pretrained model.
So So how about outcome supervision
or we can think of it as
related to reinforcement learning too.
So reinforcement learning is very, very
different than SFT.
In what sense? In the sense that
if we are just supervising the outcome instead
of the full process, entire process,
I'm just showing you this equation is showing
the gradient of the
outcome supervision or example,
reinforcement learning. So this
is very, very unstable.
This m matrix that you see here, this is
a property of the data.
And we have a edge of stability here.
If m is smaller than one, meaning
that the reinforcement learning data
or outcome supervision data or post
training data is easy for the model. The
gradient becomes smaller
exponentially with the number of thinking
steps. So if you think
more, your gradient becomes very, very small,
and you you you make progress
very, very slowly. And
if m is large, meaning that the task
is hard for the model, it becomes
very, very chaotic and unstable.
We should reduce the learning length
learning a lot.
So what is a good
data technically? So here,
again, I'm skipping a lot of the
math here. But the short
message is that the reinforcement learning
data in contrast to SFT should
not be very hard for the pretrained model.
Right? It shouldn't be trivial
but it should also not be too hard. It should
be kind of non
trivial for the model, but not very hard.
And we need a lot of that data.
We really need a large amount of reinforcement
learning data to make the training
stable such that the model can learn something
in a stable manner. Right?
Otherwise, if you have a little bit noise
in your test prompt,
or the the length of the
prompts are shorter or some
something, some sort of that kind of
situation. The model again
behaves on a stable way and it gets
into the overthinking region.
So short message is that it should be nontrivial
but not too hard, and it should be large
in contrast to SFTP.
And something that is very, very useful for
outcome supervision is that we make sure
that the pretrained model
has the knowledge of everything
as much as possible. Because this
makes your reinforcement learning
stable. Right? Otherwise, if you
do reinforcement learning on something that
is hard for the model, the model doesn't know about it.
It really becomes unstable.
You need to spend a lot of time and data
to make it stable again. And to
make it fall back into this stable region.
So the this also shows some result
on pretraining side. Pretraining
data should be diverse and balanced
and that is a high quality pretraining data.
So let me speed up a little bit here.
These are just some experiments
First row is the SFT.
Second row is outcome supervision.
First row shows the test loss on the
y axis. First plot top
left. Is versus the number
of examples for SFD. This
is the hard regime. This is the optimal regime. So
if even in the hard regime, we want the
SFD data to be small enough. Otherwise,
again, test perform test error increases.
Middle plot, same conclusion
with the length of the prongs.
Right? We also don't want them
to be too long. And the
rightmost shows that the the number of steps
of thinking would not change
the solution as much. But in
the bottom, you see the opposite. The larger the
number of prompt is, the larger the length of
front is. We get better
smaller error, better performance.
And the right one shows that
if you think more, and
the task is not good
level of difficulty for the pretrained
model, your model gets worse samples.
Okay. So kind of very opposite
conclusions from SFT or RL we have from
Optimization. So this
is also a small real world experiment.
So what probably we can focus
on is that, of course, SFD high
quality data, hard and diverse is much
better than random. SFT data.
But something that is interesting is that
in this regime, hard and diverse,
if we increase the size of SFD
data, the performance
slightly drops. Compared to second to
the last and the last row. So this
is kind of a confirmation for the previous
slide synthetic experiments.
But, what what is the how how is
the heart and diverse being measured, like,
for So here, I
will show you at the end of the talk
how we can put this data together.
But for the sake of, this experiment,
you can think of using a language
model to label that difficulty label
for different SFT existing SFT data.
Like, we have a existing,
supervised fine tuning data. This is for medical
reasoning m tune m 23
k. We can use a language model to
label the difficulty of this
problems, medical problems, from one to
five. And this is the hardest.
Or most difficult level.
And diverse
again, I will show you how we can find. But
this is kind of closer to the
first case, which is the optimal case.
Okay. So let me contact you and
also talk two, three minutes about test
time scaling. When do we get improvement
from test time scaling and when we do not?
So again, if we
use the previous setting, the in context linear
regression, for our
transformer, if we analyze that,
are two takeaways. That we can
observe. First is that
if your post training task
if your, sorry, inference
task are talking about test time scaling.
If your test task or inference
task, which the model thinks for a long time and
answer it, If
this task is something that the model knows
about, then then you
can just increase
the test time compute and improve
the performance of your model or in this case,
reduce the test error of it.
Right? So test time is scaling works, and it works
great. And there's a trade off. You can
spend less time during
training and you can spend your compute
at test time just using
test time scaling, and you can recover the performance.
So you can decide whether to spend
your compute for training or test, and both
of them work pretty well.
But if the model does not
know about your test time
task, then the more you think
you make the performance
worse and worse. Right?
So if your test task is hard for
the model, do not think about
it. Too long. Because you
just fall into this overthinking
regime. That you just degrade the performance further
and further. So
test time scaling helps about
things that the model know about.
Otherwise, we just fall into we start
reasoning about
something incorrectly and we just keep continue
making the situation worse and worse.
Okay. So again, some quick real world experiments.
Here, we are having two mathematical reasoning tasks.
One of them is GCD, greatest
common division. And one of them
is finding polynomial roots.
So we have the Cuban 2.57
b as the base model. And we
train it once on GCD and once on poly.
Separately. These two tasks are not aligned with each
other. The test for
all these table is GCD.
Right? During test time, we do test time scaling
for GCT. And if
you compare the QN base versus QN
poly, both of them are tested on GCD.
If the model thinks less
up to one k, the
performance of the cubic poly
becomes slightly worse than the Cuban base.
Right? We are training on Poly. We are testing on
GCD. These two are not related, so
we performance to go down.
But if the model thinks more,
like two k, the performance
becomes significantly worse.
Right? So if you are training on something and testing
on something that is not covered in your
training, if you take think more, you
make the situation worse and worse.
Right? So this is kind of a confirmation of this
theoretical result I was explaining.
And does this mean that
like in the previous slide, I said that if
things are aligned, which we are in the good case,
test time is scaling is gonna
work. We don't need to spend as much time
in training. It actually mean
that training, thinking during training
doesn't help?
So one quickest slide, no.
Thinking during training helps actually.
Even if we do not see the performance
improvement from thinking more during training
time for in distribution task,
training, with thinking
like, at training time, thinking at training time
helps OOD performance.
Which is also very useful and
interesting. So there is this trade off
between training time compute and test time compute.
We can train less and scale
compute during test time.
But there is this particular benefit of
scaling compute during training time
and thinking more for OOD performance.
Right, which is also very interesting.
Okay. So let me kind of contact you
each and try to wrap up
also for the last part. I said
that I'm going to talk about some empirical
data curation method based on the results that
I was thinking on earlier. On the
theoretical side. So how can we
curate high quality resending data?
So let's just start with SFT.
For SFT, we said that we
need a small number of hard
examples and diverse examples
for the pretrained pretrained model.
So how people actually generate this
reasoning traces in practice for training
reasoning models? Either
we do them manually which
is obviously does not scale,
or we just generate a lot of reasoning
traces from a reasoning model.
For example, DeepSick, Right?
And then we filter these examples.
For difficulty and diversity.
For example, for difficulty, we
ask a language model to label the
difficulty of these given questions from one
to five. One is easy, five is hard.
And for difficulty, we come up with some sort
of an arbitrary categorization. And again,
we ask a language model to label every example.
What is the category for this example?
And then we try to select the diverse and
difficult subset of these reasoning data
to kind of make it smaller and
higher quality. And then we train
a language model on these reasoning traces
with SF and then the language model will
be able to reason.
So As you can imagine, because these reasoning
traces are very, very long, this
is super slow. Right?
We need to generate all those huge
amount of reasoning tracers first.
Which are very long, and then we need to filter them
again with LLMs. So this entire process
is very, very slow. So
can we do better? Can
we generate the first part of the
reasoning change Very small part
of the initial part of it.
And we are able to say, oh, this is gonna be very
good. Let's keep generating the rest or no,
this is not gonna be beneficial. Let's throw it
away and move on. With another example.
So if we can do this, this is going to
speed up things a lot. This is
gonna be very beneficial.
So can we do this?
And interestingly, unfortunately, yes.
We can do this. How can we do this?
So I'm going to show you, like,
a brief overview of
the pipeline that we have. This is gonna be
on archive very soon in a few days.
So we are going to look at the first
100 tokens. I will explain
how. And then we can immediately
filter these examples without
using any LLM for difficulty.
And then for the difficult examples, we can
generate one k more tokens.
And we can immediately filter for diversity
again without having to use language
models to label categories. And
then we can only focus on generating
high quality ASR. SFD data. And
this is much faster than the existing
approaches. What's the idea? Let me
just go over it quickly for a second
of time. The idea is that when we do
fine tuning in general, for
reasoning or instruction tuning or in general, any
type of fine tuning, the
loss is much smoother. We are kind of in
a very flat regime, much
flatter compared to pre training.
Right? This is a smooth this is much
flatter. The
landscape optimization is much nicer.
So you can think of a quadratic.
Region. In this quadratic region,
what we found out is that if you
take your pretrained model and you pair
with random noise, a couple
of times, you can
technically model or simulate
checkpoints during SFD
training. Somehow because this is
quadratic. Just perturb your
pretrained model, you can cover all these level
sets of the loss. Right.
This is very high level, of course.
But now how can we use these three train
checkpoints? First, for difficulty,
the first, 100 tokens
of every reasoning trace these are
kind of rephrasing the question. Model is trying to understand
what was the question. That you just
asked at the beginning of the reasoning.
So we evaluate the loss of
this one hundred one hundred
first initial tokens after reasoning trace,
on a highly perturbed checkpoints.
Random checkpoint. Right? The
as long as the perturbation is large enough,
we can just divide separate to,
all the examples into high loss and low
loss. And then they just
get rid of the low loss.
Examples and these are the easy examples.
This shows that the model knows these questions
pretty well. But if the loss is high,
the model does not know the question. As
well. So these are hard questions.
So immediately we can filter hard
questions. And this plot shows
that we
difficulty labeling, that is the x axis,
there is a very good correlation with the
between the
five, like, the number on the x axis,
and the green. Dark
green bars. Which is what we did.
So this is difficulty. We can do it
very fast. And easy.
How about diversity? For diversity,
we can prove that if two
examples, if two reasoning traces have similar
value for the loss on all these
randomly perturbed check points, then they have
similar gradients. During
fine tune. And this
is nice because gradient diversity
is usually the best measure for diversity
you can have compared to heuristics
or other stuff. So
we generate the first one k tokens
and then we calculate the loss of them
on all these perturbed checkpoints.
So if you have five checkpoints, we
will have a loss vector of size
five for every example.
Then we are clustering this low dimensional
loss vectors, examples within every
cluster are guaranteed to have similar gradients.
So we can already get clusters
of examples with similar gradient and
sample a diverse subset. And this is
after only generating one take
one k token alpha, for example, 100
k tokens. So we
have difficulties We examples, we filter
them for diversity as well. We
directly know which examples are good to generate
further. So So
this is just showing that one case is
enough. Like, no matter what is your perturbation,
the blue and
red shows the
kind of shows that loss doesn't change after
one k or two k tokens.
And then we are good to use one k.
Okay. So
what if we apply this, method to
two reasoning tasks, One is medical reasoning.
Second one is mathematical reasoning.
Open thoughts on m 22 k.
So I'm not going to explain colors
but you can look at compare these
final bars left and right. Compare
this blue region here in the
end with the full thing.
So this is the cost of this method
versus like, generating everything and
filtering them. So less than
10% of the cost, we can directly generate
a high quality SFV data. Which is
very useful. How about performance?
Performance comparing to existing
kind of baselines. You can see that this
orange line is doing much better
than other existing baselines in
including LMM filtering, which is the dash
blue. This is finding
one k out of 23 k for medical
reasoning. And the model is q
one two point five seven b. X
axis is the size of the subset.
So this is working really nice.
It also works well the last
row if you compare with all the open models that
are trained on much larger datasets.
This is also working much
working pretty well compared to them.
And this is something very interesting.
So previous slide, we were applying this method to select
among existing reasoning traces.
This slide, we applied it to generate new
reasoning traces. So we ask
for example, q w q, this is the
problem, generate some reasoning. We
look at the 100 tokens and we look at the
one k tokens and directly know if
this is gonna be a good generation or not. So we
are generating from scratch And
we are comparing with OpenThink Care. OpenThink
Care is this model that is trained
this is math reasoning only. Trained on almost
90 k reasoning traces
generated with the same model, dot q w q.
We So after only generating five
k, we can get the same
performance. As OpenThinker, which is
trained on 90 ks. Reasoning traces.
Right? And this is way faster like
10% less than 10% of the time.
Which is really nice.
So all the base models for all of these rows
is Q1 2.5. And these
are different evaluations on different math
benchmarks. Amy Matt
blah blah. Okay.
So one more slide I'm going to show you. How about our
L data curation? So here
I know that I do not have time to cover this. Just
I'll show you the results. So
for RL, from the theoretical perspective,
we know that the level of difficulty should be
right. It should not be too easy or it should not
be too hard. So in
particular, for example, for GRPO,
examples that have
high STD of rewards for
the generations of GRPO. These are good
examples. In terms of difficulty.
But the issue is that we need to generate all
these reasoning traces for
every example, and then we need to revert them, and then
we need to calculate the STP of the reward.
And this is very slow. So
here, what we did is that for every example,
we first generate two rollouts.
We see which ones are high HDD. Only
for those examples, we generate four rollouts.
We see which ones have higher STD.
For those examples, only we generate more
robots. So we are spending the
rollout generation for
the most beneficial examples only.
And the numbers are, I think, a little bit
small, but this shows that we
can generate up to 50%
smaller number of rollouts. And
still find the examples with good level of difficulty
for training math
reasoning. Again, different cube and sizes, 1.5
b, 2.5 b, seven b,
and five four. This is
for math reasoning compared to all the baselines,
compared green with other
ones if you can see. And also
for quote.
Kind of generating
coding. Was all. Thank you so much. I'm happy
to take questions either right now or
later offline. Thanks
so much. Yeah. Thanks,
Bahareh. So, if you have any questions,
feel free to come to the, the, yeah, in
the middle.
Thanks a lot. I really enjoyed
intuition for the last line of this type of diversity versus
hardness. My concern is that how
are you making sure that this is no overlap?
Given the fact that if there is a small overlap,
that would be very helpful. I didn't see that.
For SFTP? Right. For which
part? For SFT data generation, how do
we make sure there is no overlap? There is no overlap with the
pretrained data, which you don't have access to.
Uh-huh. So examples that are have high
loss for the pretrained model that is
per terp these are difficult for
the pretrained model. Yeah. But there
might be, like, which overlap still. Right?
Doing our best to minimize that overlap as
much as possible, technically. So
if you select hardest questions,
you are doing your best to do minimal overlap.
Like the questions are given usually.
Right? Among those given questions, you are going
for the best. You are going for the hardest.
But still there might still be in the
big overlap. Right? Not on the the two
other side of the system. If there is nothing that has
like hard loss really, I think that that is not
a good set of questions to start with.
Thanks. Yeah.
Thanks. Any other question?
I have a. Thanks for the great talk.
Like, when you show the SFT figures,
what are these spikes? What
That is double descent. That is versus the
length of the number of prongs.
And that is the double descent. As you increase,
the loss goes down, goes up and then goes down
again which falls into the good region.
Oh, why why do we why does it go
up? So it's the double
descent as you increase the for example, there is
double descent phenomenon as you increase the
number of parameters in a model or as you increase
in our case, number of training
examples. The proofs
are in the paper. Okay. Okay. Okay. So
it's like
But the spikes looks pretty big.
Like, I'm not sure if it's it's
normal or not. I just So the y
axis was sluggish. Okay. Okay.
So we made it also look bigger. I see. Thanks.
Sure.
Have a question about this, linear regression
problem that you mentioned. So linear
regression is usually numerical,
like numbers. Right? Yes.
But, in LLMs or in this case,
like, how are you making sure that, this numerical
aspect is properly
captured, through that organization? So we
are getting all the insights from linear
regression? And the insights we kind
of show that they hold in practice for
language model strength and natural
language. I see.
Thank you for the great talk. Pratyusha from
NVIDIA. I just wanted to ask
about an interesting result about
correlation between the difficulty graded by
Gemini
And, I'm wondering what the takeaway there is. Is that,
you know, more about the the parameter
space being smooth? Is that about the ability
for out of domain generalization? Could you maybe
walk through what the takeaways are? For that one, we are
just saying that you do not need Gemini. You
do not need other language models.
Just measure the loss of the first 100
tokens of your reasoning trace.
On the pretrained check like, perturb the pretrained
checkpoint by some random noise.
And then measure the loss of the first 100
tokens of your reasoning trace on that
perturbed checkpoint. And you can already
know which one is difficult, which one is not. You
do not need any extra LLM.
Measure the difficulty. Was showing that there
is a very high correlation between this approach
and if you use to do
difficulty between. Thank you. Yeah.
Okay. Yeah. So, thanks a lot
for, Baharin.
Yeah. So, and
let's move to another
the second, MITRE talk by, Siewan.
So, Si Wang is assistant
professor in ECS
UC Berkeley affiliated with
Bayer and a research scientist at
AirTwo. Her research focuses on the
understanding and advancing the large language
models with a goal
of improving their performance
flexibility, and adaptability.
And, flexibility.
Yeah. So, today, I shall talk about
flex OM. Yeah. Let's welcome, Siu.
Thank you for the invitation.
Hi, everyone. Thanks for coming. I'm
Siouan, and I'm very excited
to be here and share my thoughts
on one of the core
data problems in foundation models, which is
fragmented data. So
in this talk, I'll talk about what I mean by fragmented
data. Why it matters, and
what do we do with that. This is,
based on the work jointly done with Weija,
and Kevin, as well as many
others. Okay.
So let me get started with a broader question.
Will we continue to benefit from scaling
foundation models?
I believe the answer to this is debatable.
But it is useful to think about
if the answer turns out to be no,
then what is the reason?
At a high level, scaling depends
on two factors. Data
and compute.
So We have a brief good
sense that compute is getting too
cheaper and is getting more accessible
over time, so maybe compute is not a problem.
But data is a different story.
We hear that data is running
out. Internet data is finite.
And the speed that we generate
data may not be
faster than the speed we want model capabilities
to grow. So data is a real bottleneck.
When it comes to data running out, we think
about the quantity of the data and
we have been doing great research on
topics like synthetic data generation
to increase the data. But
in this talk, I wanna offer a different
perspective.
Maybe in terms of quantity,
we are we are fine. We in fact
may have a lot of data. But
the real problem is the data in
the world is fragmented.
Meaning these are the data sets owned by
different institutions or different entities.
And there is no single central
entity that have centralized access
to all the datasets. But
So what does it exactly mean? So we
all know that valuable datasets
are critical for foundation model training. They
should be high quality, they should be
broad coverage, very
diverse in domains.
But also, valuable data such are often
not public. Valuable
data sets are often restricted,
private, or proprietary
that some institutions or entities may own
and may not want to share for public
use. There could
be many different reasons for that, they may
have want to retain having full control
over the data or having full
value of the data. And
some examples include corporate
code, some textbooks owned by
publishers, internal documentations,
or medical record. And you
can see there are often on
highly specialized domains, which are
actually very important because nowadays foundation
models are increasingly targeting those
specialized domain. So
On top of that, data
that used to be public is now
increasingly getting closed.
This is a graph from a paper called Consonant Crisis
that shows that data
that used to be included in common crawl which
is public, is now getting closed
because data owners do not want to
use their data for public use.
So this means even data that used to
be public is closing the news
public data is not just not growing,
but also shrinking. So this is
a big problem. So
what do I do in terms of model training?
So let's start with reviewing
how current LLM training works.
So we gather data from many different
sources, but we typically treat it as one
set of data. We just gather all
of them into a single set, We
randomly shuffle them, and we use it
to train a single giant model.
So this is great, but this assumes
there is a single entity,
which is a model developer that has
centralized access to all the data.
However, in reality, that's not really
true because datasets are
fragmented. They're distributed. They are owned
by different entities. And current
training doesn't really support scenario.
So that's kind of the main claim in this talk,
which is we really need a
new training recipe for LLM
that can benefit from fragmented
data. Okay.
So now how do we do that? So
we had a proposal that is about modular
distributed training and here's how
it works. So we first have a
public model that is
trained on public data only like Common Core.
Then we also there is a set of data owners
who have their own data locally.
They can take this public model and then
do continuous training on their data
locally. So this training is
completely in isolation, completely independent.
And they never share the data to public,
the data is always local.
Once this training is done, then
they still don't share data, but they can share
model parameters. And we can combine
it into a single unified model.
So this proposal have two unique properties.
First, it allows data owners to be
able to contribute to AI
training without needing to share the raw data. So
they can still retain full control
over the data. They can retain full
value of the data.
Now other thing is as you can see, this
training is completely modular. That means
adding data or removing the data is
very easy. For instance, if one
data owner want to
and put it to the
combined model. If one of the
data owners that used to participate wanna opt
out later on, we can do that simply by
removing parameters contributed by
data owner. And the rest of the model is
guaranteed not to use any of that data.
So this is nice. But how
do we actually achieve this? What is our actual
technical solution? So let's consider
all the options. Let's start with, modern
emerging techniques. So
model merging is broadly useful for merging
a few different models in our case,
we have one public model, and then
let's say three models trained
four of them. And then we can combine
them into a single model using weight
averaging called model soup.
Or doing ensemble. These
model merging techniques are actually
already being used as a standard practice
for boosting model performance. But
typically, these models are trained on
near identical data sets, but
with slightly different distribution.
We found that actually in our case,
things are a little different because datasets
from different data owners are completely disjoint
datasets. And can have very different
distribution. And we found model merging
doesn't work in this case
because when models are trained on completely
disjoint datasets, their model
weight can diverge so much that
it becomes very difficult to merge.
So that what do we do? So we consider
second option, which is MOE merging.
And to talk about MOE merging, we should
first talk about
k. So this is a model that is
not on MOE. We call it a dense model.
So it has a few small layers like multi
annotation and then on FFmpeg.
And usually, consists of the majority of parameters.
Now what Mixr of Experts does is
to replace this FFN
into a set of small FFNs
many small FFNs called expert,
and then also a router. So how it
works is only a subset of those
router. And
DTM was our very standard architecture
in all frontier models now,
They use it because
of compute efficiency. You can see
here that MOE have nice modular
architecture So our goal is can we
actually benefit from this modular architecture?
So what we wanna do is something like this.
So again, we have to four models,
and we want to merge it into a single
MOE. We do that by keeping
every FFN separate, so
we can keep the x coming
from each data owner as it is. And
then do weight weight averaging for
the shared layers like multi attention
and so on. And then we had a router
later on. So first of all,
this architecture is actually exactly identical
to the standard m way, which is
a great thing because we can reuse
the existing infrastructure for
MOE serving or inference. That's a great
thing. However, there is a problem,
which is, as you can see, model
training is done as a dense model. So
this model actually never
learned how to be an MOE model. So
typically, you need to further
train on MOE after merging, showing
to the overall data set. However,
that's not really applicable in our setup.
Because we assume datasets
are completely disjoint and fragmented.
No single entity can have access to
all the datasets. So now
the question is,
MOE but remove the need for joint
data apps?
Is that clear?
Cool. Okay. So we came over a couple
of techniques to deal with this
issue. One of them is what we call
learning to coordinate. And this
is how it works. So when a data owner
does their own training, they
take the dense model, And instead
of doing regular continual training, which would
override the model weight, we are going
to actually make it on MOE with two
experts. And in particular, we
are going to freeze
the first FFN as well as all the shared
layers and only keep the second
FFN trainable. Gonna talk about
the router later on, so let's forget about the
router for now. So you
can see that this is actually identical
to having the the
the public model as it is as an
anchor model. It's frozen.
But then just add an additional FFN
to be trained on this
their local data sets. So it's
kind of learning how to coordinate
and learning how to work as an MOE
by using this public model as an anchor.
Once this training is completed, this data owner
can just contribute the second
back to the public space and we
can merge it into a single MOE.
By keeping each FFN from
different different data owners as an MOE.
And we don't have to do anything with about
the shared layers because they're already synchronized.
They're already identical to the public model.
So they already kind of know how to work together.
So this is good. Now we haven't talked
about the routers. So what do we do with the
router? So router is essentially
an N Way classifier. It involves a
made matrix that is n by d, where n
is a number of experts and d
is hidden dimension. So what we can
do is to decompose this
router matrix into
n number of d dimensional
embeddings, which we call router embeddings. And
each router embedding correspond to each
expert. So we have our pop that correspond
to the public FFN, r one,
r two, and r three.
So where do they come from? They can come from
each data owner's training. When it's data
owner does their own training, they
have this MOE with two experts.
That means they were going to have two router
embeddings. They can use
domain embedding from their data. So they
have our pop, which is a domain embedding
for a public model. Public
data that is frozen And then
there is R1, which is a domain embedding
for their data We can keep it trainable.
So when they do their training, it's essentially
still keeping the public model as
the anchor model. But trained two
additional component, FFN and
r one. And once that training
is done, they contribute this R1
to the public space game. We
can concatenate all the router embeddings from
every data owner and form it a
single and that can be readily
available as a router.
So that's kinda how it works. So just
putting things together, we start
with the stance model that is public
model. Then each data owner takes
it, and add a second
FFN as well as router embedding to do their
own training. Using the
public model as an anchor model. And
then after their training is done, they contribute
FFN as router embedding. And we can make it
as a single mixture
of expert model that is read a little bit
by doing combination, We
keep each separate. We concatenate
all the router embeddings to make it an
NWE. And again, this is exactly
identical to the standard MOE RTT
so we can reuse a lot of things.
Now As I briefly hinted earlier,
because it's training as model alert, that means
opt in and opt out is very
easy. So for instance, let's say one of our
data owners is New York Times,
They used to participate, but they wanna opt out
later on. Then we can simply do
that by removing the parameters
contributed by neural times.
And it's guaranteed that none
of the rest of the parameter is using
your times data in any way.
Cool. Okay. So that was a model. Now
let's move on to experiments.
So designing experimental setup for
this work was very hard because we need
some public data and some private
data sets, proprietary data sets.
Those private data sets are by definition private,
so we don't have access to them. But
we still wanted to simulate the most realistic
scenario as much as possible.
So we came up with some setup.
So we have public data that is common
crawl. This is an Internet data that is actually
public. And then we define
seven data sets that we consider to
be proprietary.
One thing that is kind of nice is
actually three of them are
actual proprietary datasets. They used
to be public, that's why we still had
them downloaded on our
our computer. But now data owners
close their data, so it's no longer
public. It's proprietary. So we
use those datasets. The other
four datasets are public, such simulated
proprietary data sets, but we also
chose domains in a way that they
reflect realistic scenarios. So
for instance, we included code because
corporate code is representative
case. Included
papers because a lot of publishers actually
don't release the data
for public use.
Okay. And these are some training details. I'm
not going to go over all the details, but
just to highlight a few, we trained our
7,000,000,000 parametric model.
We trained from scratch
because we wanted to make sure the base
model is guaranteed to only train
on public data. But if
you take any open weight model, it's
hard to guarantee that. So we had to
train a model ourselves. So we'd pre
train a model from scratch
on public data for 1,000,000,000,000 tokens.
And then we assume each of
the seven data owners
does continual pretraining
over 50,000,000,000 tokens each.
So that's the setup. Here are the
results. So in the paper, we included
over 30 different
benchmarks. Here, I'm just going to show four
numbers. Two of them
are generic general purpose benchmarks.
Like MML Pro and AGILE.
Also have a domain specific benchmark on
math domain. This math two
is actually the average of two math benchmarks.
And then we also have an average of 30
benchmarks. This
is a public model that is trained on public
data only. So
in some sense, this is strictly
our baseline. Because if you
don't have our thing, then this will be
the only model we would have access to.
Right? And then we
also compare with specialized
experts. That means the
data that is trained on
local private data, but individually.
Not altogether, for each of the
domain data. We included three of them.
And what we found is when benchmarks
are in distribution to those
data owners' data, then it helps a
lot. For instance, you can see the math
expert getting a really good performance on
math benchmarks. However, when benchmarks
are not in domain, when it's out
of domain, then the performance can be much
worse. So So on average,
the performance gain is not much.
Then we also compare with prior
model merging base lines, including
model soup with those parameter
averaging. BTM, which does unsungpling,
and BTX which uses MOE.
So what we found is first of
all, overall, model margin kind of
helps. If you look at the average numbers, there are
always better than the public model,
so it means it's kind of promising, but
not as much. And
in particular, if you look at the bars
for the math benchmarks, we can
see that even though the
data the model frame of math data had
a very good performance gain,
when they were combined with other experts, the performers
dropped a lot. So that means, even
though model merging kind of helps
when you are merging multiple models,
You're kinda losing the benefit
that was that was obtained by
its individual expert.
So it's kind of not as satisfying.
And finally, here is our model, which is
called FlexOLMOM. And is
actually getting a very good performance. It's outperforming
all the models. And in particular, if you
look at the math benchmark, it can
retain the full benefit coming
from training on math data, which is kinda
exciting. We also have a pretty
good benefit on generic
benchmark like MMLU Pro and AI developed,
is likely because those benchmarks contain
a lot of subsets coming from different
domains, and therefore,
our models that can combine,
datasets coming from diverse domains
kind of help. So on average, we're getting
about 41 relative gain.
Over the public model.
What I found personally more exciting
is we actually also compare with an
upper bound model that is called unrestricted
MOE. This means we upcycle
our public model to make it on MOE.
And then we assume we have
joint access across all the
datasets and do joint training across
all of them. So this is on upper bound
because this is, like, actually
not permitted in our case, but we just wanted to
estimate the upper bound. And of course,
this upper bound is better than all the models
we have because tune training is
indeed very helpful. But our model
is actually close. We're actually
retaining over 90% of the
benefit of full training
This means, if you are willing to pay
for 10% of performance gains,
then you can get a lot of very
exciting functionalities such as modular
training, keeping the data
private, and being able to obtain and
opt out almost for free.
And finally, we have kind of like
nice opt out experiments. So here, the dark
bar is our combined model with
eight x and then the
lighter one is when we opt out one of
the experts coming from use So
what we see is, of course, on benchmark
related to news, we are getting performance drop,
which is kind of expected. But for
other datasets, we are getting a similar result.
That means even if you opt out one of the
data owners it overall have minimal
impact especially to other domains.
Cool. So, this is the
it. So I will just
wrap up with a few takeaways.
So in the beginning of the talk, I motivated
this challenge of data running out.
And then said, oh, it might not be the quantities.
Insufficient. It might be data sets are fragmented.
They're owned by different entities and cannot be
shared. So we need a new
training recipe that can benefit from this fragmented
data. So we
our proposal was to leverage the
modular architecture of MOE
but then modify the training algorithm
to benefit from fragmented data set.
And in particular, we
have different experts, different FFMs
to be trained independently by each
data owner completely in isolation,
and then they can contribute parameters
and we can combine them into a single
MoE model. And there were a few technical
challenges. I had to make it MOE aware,
so we came up with some in
and we were training and nonparametric model.
And our results show that it outperforms
training on public data only, It
approaches during training on all data sets,
which is an upper bound, and provide
free opt out, and also in.
Yeah. So I don't think the problem is solved,
of course, from this single work,
and there are many open problems to be solved.
I'll just talk about a
few commonly asked questions when
I shared this work. So one
of the common last question is does it work
for post training? Our answer used
to be no because this was all about pre training.
But very recently, in fact, earlier
this week, we released a new preprint
that shows that, oh, it works
for post training to some degree. You need to motivate
the recipe a little bit, but with some modification
it works, so check it out.
The other problem that is actually a bigger
problem is inference cost. So you
might have realized earlier already,
but as you have an additional
data owner, you need all whole new
FFN And because FFN
is a majority of parameters, it means
the inference cost can grow very
quickly. We don't want that. So
can we make it more efficient?
And in particular, can we do more fine grained
distributed learning so that growing can be a little
more incremental? Just need a little
longer discussion I think the short
answer is Yeah.
Short answer is yes conceptually,
but this first require having a
base model that is an MOE In
particular, this MOE has to be fine grained,
and it also has to be modular, meaning
it expert is already kind of specialized
in terms of domains rather than
superficial lexical cues, which
we don't really have right now.
We are working on it, and in fact, I'm giving
another talk at another workshop
tomorrow on this, like, motor and weight
topic. So if you're interested in, please check it out.
Yeah. That's it. Thank you for listening.
Yeah. Thanks, Si Wang. If you have any
questions, feel free to come to the
middle.
Hi. Thanks for a great talk.
Have one question about the datas.
It's not sure.
Can you hear me? Oh, yes. Yeah. So
I have one question about the data sizes
that you're using for the different experts.
So I think all of them were trained on the same amount
of data, but in practice,
some domains might have a lot, some might be very
scarce. Do you have any results on, like,
how much imbalance can this method handle?
Yeah. That's a very great question.
Oh, yeah. We train all experts
on the 50,000,000,000 to tokens. In
fact, we have some domains where the data set
side was smaller, but in that case, we just repeat
it. But I think it can be smaller than
that, so I think it's an important question.
We didn't have answers to that in this work.
In fact, I think that is very relevant
to the fine grained MOE that I
mentioned because if data owner with very
small data still wanna participate,
then that means each expert has to be a little
small, meaning you need to have a
finer grain MOE. And,
the second question I have is around, like,
when you train these experts,
on private data, but then eventually
release them to the general public,
there's threats around, like, could people do
in membership inference attacks or data extraction
attacks and get out private data?
Do you have any thoughts on how likely are they
or do they not work at all in
this setup? Yeah. I think that's a very great question.
We also got many questions.
So yes, there is a risk
that even if you don't share the raw data, if
you're sharing model parameters, people
can do membership inference or extraction
attack to extract some data.
We empirically validated, and I think this
is in consistent this is
consistent with literature
that when we try to do that, we can
identify it's possible to extract
less than 1% of the data, but not more
than that, meaning they're very small amount.
But I think this risk is real. What
I would say is if your
data I think there can be many meanings of
private data. If your data is private
because it's sensitive,
meaning even 1% of extracted
data can be risky, then I think you
maybe shouldn't use this approach.
Because still sharing the parameter is
problem. However, if your data is private,
because the data is valuable,
then I think that means,
oh, if we're constructing 1% of
data doesn't really matter, so in that case you can
use that. So I think we can use this
approach mainly for the latter case.
Makes sense. Thanks a lot for the talk.
Thank you very much for your talk. I had a question
about in part from
this mathematical dataset that you showed that
there is a big benefit
for them, But
if you were the owner of these datasets,
that is very specialized and high valued
for your problem. There is no benefit
for them to share So I see why
the others are gaining, but
this actor is not gaining
anything. So what do you think about
this kind of value proposition
for them? Why would they bring their
dataset in? Yeah. I think that's a really
great question as well because this incentive problem is a
real issue. I think there could be two main
scenarios that they might wanna share. One
is they do want to
collaborate with other data owners. First, they
may have good data math data, but they don't have
good good data. Maybe there's another data
owner that have good good data, but not
math. If they just
alone, they can't just do their work, but if they
collaborate, they can do a better job. So I think it can
be a way to collaborate with other
entities. The second scenario
which is a little less tech technically is I
think this can be a new
avenue for data licensing or even data
market. Data market is
already a thing. People purchase the data
by giving
yeah, People purchase the
data, but then they have to share the raw
data. Think this can be another way of data
market where they share the parameters trained
on their data. Without needing to share
the raw data because that's less risky.
Actually I I actually actually, like like, right now, it's the
the the cough cough bridge. Yeah. So maybe
okay.
Questions too. I have a pretty quick question.
So have you tried, like, not
using the fine grained experts or,
like, kinda
adding more depend? With the specialized
data. But instead, training
the model with the public
and specialized data to generate synthetic
and then using that in in your final mix.
Doesn't make improvements or
usually, like, if you have a specialized
model, and synthetic will be kinda
not specialized anymore?
Just to confirm my understanding, so you
mean how does it relate
it based on whether it's real data versus
So basic can you can you try to generate
a specialized kind of synthetic data and adding to
the mix? I see.
Yeah. Good question. Yeah. We haven't
really looked at the synthetic data. I think
looking into that would be very valuable. My
fence is if this is a
domain the base model has never seen at
all, then generating domain
specific synthetic data will be very
a already have some data,
and then the model already kind of know the domain,
but they want to increase the quantity. But
if it's a very unique data, then synthetic
data might not be able to
replace the real data. That's what I'm
thinking.
Okay. Yeah. Let's, thank, Seungun
again.
Great. We'll we'll have a a corporate break,
right now, and, we'll be back at
10:30.
Hi, everyone. So, please
come back. We will start for our
first
oral talk.
Alright. So, thanks for,
coming, for the, the workshops.
The second session, in
the this morning is, oral presentations.
So the first oral presentation will be
by, May, who'll
introduce, omics.
Let's welcome, May.
Hello? Oh, okay. There we go.
Okay. Hi, everyone. My name is Mei Yi,
and I'll be presenting OMICS,
which is a data mixing framework I worked on
while I was interning at AI2.
So in data mixing, you have
many different pretraining domains. So here
we have web math
and code. And your goal is to figure out how to
combine training data from all of them, such
that your model exhibits a broad variety
of capabilities. Currently,
the naive approach is just brute force
search or tuning the ratios manually.
So this requires a bunch of trial and error,
which is but there
are also many recent mixing methods that
learn data mixes more efficiently.
Today, rather than talking about a new
mixing method, I'm going to focus on issues
that arise in data mixing during model
development. So consider this timeline
here, so you're on the left,
maybe a few months or weeks out from the day
you want to start pre training your big model,
And you have your domains and you want to figure
out the data mix.
So So the first question is how do I
get a good mix on these domains
that I start out with? And it's not
super clear what to do, so should you run
some existing mixing method out
of the box? Should you build your own method?
And so that's the first challenge, and this is
sort of what we faced at the start of
building the Omo three model.
So Second, let's suppose we figured out the
initial mix and next challenge
is that data is constantly
changing throughout model development. And
this is just reality, so people are
constantly building new data sets, or they
might be refining some other data sets,
and so the question becomes how do you maintain
a good mixture throughout development?
So let's get into the first part of
the talk, As some background on the data
mixing problem, we have
m training domains, d one through d
m, and we want to train a model of
s parameters on r tokens.
And the data mix p is a probability
vector over the m domains
and the final mixed training dataset is created by
sampling r times p
of I tokens for each domain d I.
We then denote l m of r
p as a target model trained according
to data p. And we evaluate
this trained model on end tasks
where we measure bits per byte also
known as BPB, so lower is better here.
And the goal in data mixing is to
efficiently find the mix that minimizes
the average BPB over all the
downstream tasks.
So there are many mixing methods that aim
to solve this problem I just described, and
a lot of them actually follow this general template
which we call offline mixing
schema. The first step is we train
a bunch of smaller models, and we
call these proxy models on different mixes,
and we then evaluate each of models
on the tasks we care about. So we're
refer to this as a swarm of proxy
models. Next,
using the swarm, we're going to fit a
regression model that learns the relationship between
the mixing ratios and the performance.
This regression model, this f hat
of p, is going to allow us to predict the performance
of any data mixture.
Finally, we propose a mix by
solving an optimization problem that uses the
regression model as a surrogate for true down
performance. Basically, we find the mix that
has the best predictive performance.
These are the three steps of the offline
mixing schema, and so the question is,
how do we construct a good mixing
method from from this general procedure?
So by examining this schema, we came
up with a list of questions that a
practitioner needs to go through in order to instantiate
a mixing method. For the sake of
time, I'll only be presenting the three bolded
questions, So first, in constructing
the swarm, you need to determine how
big these proxy models are and how many
of them you need. And then for the regression
fitting, the obvious question is what regression
model to use. You can also take a look
at our paper to see how we investigate a bunch
of other design choices.
To study each design choice, our target
models are 1,000,000,000 parameters
trained on 100,000,000,000 tokens,
and we experimented on DCLM baseline,
a web corpus that was partitioned into
24 topic based domains. So
mixing on things like literature, politics,
science, and so on. And we measured BPB
bits per byte on a suite of 52
tasks that covered math, code, and question
answering. The first question
is proxy model size. How
small can these proxy models be so that
they still provide meaningful signal for
the 1b target models? To
study this, we took a bunch of mixture ratios,
and for each mix, we trained both a proxy
model and a target model on it. And
then we looked at the performance rankings of
these mixtures at both scales and
measured the rank correlation. Basically,
we're trying to see if the data mixtures that
did the best on small models also
do the best on large models. And we
repeat this experiment for many different proxy
model sizes.
So Here are our results. So on the x
axis is the size of the
models. We did one, 15, 30,
and 60,000,000. And on the
y axis is the rank correlation with our target
one b parameter model. We
see that everything over 15,000,000 parameters
has pretty high rank correlation.
So our recommendation is that at least to
do well at the 1b scale, we recommend
using proxy models that are over
15,000,000 parameters.
So next question is how big
the swarm should be. So concretely, if we
want to mix over m
domains, how many proxy models do we need?
For our experiment, we construct various
swarms by sweeping over m, the
number of domains, and k, the
number of proxy runs. And we measure
performance of the resulting mix relative
to the best mix per m.
This figure here shows our results
So on the x axis is the swarm size.
Where we've scaled everything not to be the absolute
size but just size relative to the number
of domains. And on the
y axis is the error, so how close
we are to the best mix we found.
And the thing to notice here is that across
all of the m's, from six
to 24 domains, the curves all look
pretty much the same. So this indicates
that error is only dependent on the
swarm size relative to the to the
number of domains. Basically, this means
that we just need O of M proxy models
to learn a good mix over
M domains. The last
question here is what regression model
should we use to capture the relationship
between the mix and downstream performance?
Study this, we take a swarm and try five different
regression models on it. These,
range from gradient boosting to Gaussian processes
to parametric functions.
We measure the regression fit of each
model on held out mixes.
And we looked at how this depends on swarm size. So
this reveals something pretty interesting, which is
that different regression models need
different amounts of data, which is something that hasn't
been exposed in prior works.
So for instance, this method, bimix,
is quite good for small swarms.
While light GBM needs much more proxy
runs. And to figure out which one we
use, we noticed that the log linear
models, which are in purple, outperform
the other models consistently once you
have at least 75 runs.
Basically at least three times the number of
domains. Also saw that
Log linear outperforms other models in downstream
performance. So our conclusion from this study
was to use the log linear regression model.
And after studying all these design choices,
we used our findings to define a
base method, Olmec space,
our recommended default configuration of the offline
mixing schema. So all the text
in pink are the modifications to the schema
based on our empirical findings.
So in this warm step, we use 30,000,000
parameter proxy models Basically,
anything above 15 is fine, and
we use o of m proxy models.
And in the regression model step, we fit
a log linear model for each task.
And finally, in the optimization step,
I wasn't able to go over this due
to time, but we added a constraint
to ensure that proposed mixes don't
extend data mixing to the data constraint
setting. So
moving into this question of how to
mix under evolving data. So
this is a pretty novel problem setting,
but we were motivated by what we saw in
practice, which is that data is consistently being
updated throughout model development.
So consider the following scenario.
You and, your team are training a
LLM and you have a pretty good mix
over your data sets and you spent some time
figuring out these ratios, but
then the data changes. So maybe
someone on your team finishes preparing a new data
set that is just so incredibly
good that you have to add it in, or you realize
that you should more aggressive
to be made. Happen and the
question is what do you do with this mix
that you've prepared on your old data sets?
I'll formally describe the problem of mixing as
data evolves now. So we start
with a domain set d of m
domains, then this is updated into
d prime, which consists of m prime
domains. Based on our
experience, we found four major ways that
D is updated into D prime.
We have addition and removal of datasets.
So these are pretty self explanatory.
We also have partition, where we take
a data set and we annotate it such that we
now have finer grained categories.
And lastly, we have revisions which can be
filtering, rewriting, and so on.
And our goal in this setting is that we are
given an existing mix
p tilde on the old set of domains d
and we want to compute the optimal mix
q star over the new set of domains
d prime efficiently.
Before I jump into our method, a simple
baseline is full recompute
This could be all mixed based, which I just
explained. Directly to d prime every
time the domain set is updated.
The problem with this is that it becomes expensive
very fast. So if your data is
changing a lot through development, this means
that you are constructing a swarm
of size o of m prime with
every update. So instead, we're going to see
how to reuse the existing mix
p tilde so we don't have to relearn everything
each time. So to
explain mixture, we use our method
let's look at this example of partitioning. So
you start with four domains, and the
fourth one gets partitioned into
two subdomains d four prime
and d five prime. Let's
give some names to these domains. So we say
we start with science, politics, literature,
and code, and then code gets split up into Python
versus not Python. And now
suppose we have some existing p tilde
ratios over these initial four
domains. Let's take
a closer look at the normalized ratios of
the first three domains, which are not impacted
by the partition at all.
The core bet we're going to make is that
these normalized ratios are still good
after a code is partitioned. Essentially,
the fact that we now have Python versus non
Python to mix over is not going
to change the relative ratios of
science versus politics, literature.
And this assumption is going to motivate us
to reuse these normalized ratios.
So let's get into the method. We
take d prime and we're going to split it into two
subsets, d fix which are the
domains that were not affected by the update,
and decomp, which are the domains that are affected by
the update. But The first
thing is that we freeze the ratios within defix,
basically treating
dFix as one giant virtual domain.
Then rather than recomputing the mix over everything,
we're only going to recomplete over what
we call the collapsed mix, which is
the a single defixed virtual
domain, as well as the affected domains.
So in this example rather than learning over
five domains, we just learn on three. Which
is going to be a simple cheaper
Finally, once we've learned the mix on three domains,
we're going to use the frozen ratios
to expand the learned mix back to
d prime. So let's look at
an example. So remember that
these were the normalized ratios of p tilde within
d fix And let's suppose that the
second step of recomputation gives us
a mix of point six on the
entire defixed virtual domain and point two five
and one five on the others.
Then we can construct the full proposed mix
by multiplying point six the
normalized ratios above. So this procedure
we're proposing is essentially up
applying a mixing method in a lower dimensional slice of
the mixture space, and the
main thing this achieves is that there's less recomputation
required.
So for evaluation, we simulate a
realistic development scenario where data
evolves over time.
Accumulate in a final data set
of six we So we
first start with a web dataset DCLM
split into 24 topics. And then
we'll do some addition, we'll revise,
remove, and partition. And
so in this setting, again, we train 1,000,000,000
parameter models and evaluate them
over 52 tasks.
Our main baseline is the natural
distribution which is just to mix proportional
to the final domain sizes. So you
can think of this as the mix that is induced
you just concatenate all your data sets
together and just sample from that.
We also consider full re computation,
which applies Omic space to
all domains after each update. And you can
think of this as roughly our upper bound on
performance. And lastly, we have our method,
make sure we use.
Our result is on the performance versus
cost trade off. So on the x axis
is the total number of proxy runs that the method
uses throughout the five updates,
and on the y axis is the
performance improvement over the natural distribution.
So methods that are in the top left corner are
the best. If we look across
horizontally, we can see that mixture
reuse achieves between
95 to 98% of full recomputation's
performance while using around
67% fewer total proxy
runs. If we look
vertically, we can see how all these methods
do when we fix the budget. So at a budget of around
200 to 300 runs,
make sure reuse achieves 12%
improvement over the natural distribution while full
recomputation achieves 10.8%
on average.
So Beyond trade offs, our best mix is three
times more data efficient than the natural distribution,
And then finally, this figure shows some of
the proposed mixes for full recomputation,
our best mix, and the natural distribution.
We can see that our proposed mix
is more similar to full recomputation than
distribution, aligns with the downstream performance
results from the previous slides.
So So to quickly wrap
things up, our paper, OMIC has
two main contributions. So first
is a study of the core
So
And second is a mixture reuse
method that allows us to efficiently
adjust data mixes even when the data changes
as we develop the model.
Here are some future directions. So
we primarily consider static mixes,
so we're not doing any sort of like online
mixing or curriculum, but this would be another
interest how
evolvingness to consider. And
then another direction for future work
I've been thinking about is codesign with
other data development stages. So
for instance, how do we use mixture
performance to inform decision making
on what what domains
you need more data of?
Finally, these these are the
slides, and we also have
in our paper some more design choices
We have, theory on when mixture
we use works well, and we have some extensions
our method. I'll take any questions or
wrap up now.
Thanks, Amy.
Thank you so much. I have a question. So
when were you do update of
the mixture? When you reuse some
of the frozen mix before, do you
still use log linear, or it's better
to use different methods? Because now we have
smaller swarm, basically.
We still use the log linear model.
But we do check and the regression fit is
still pretty good if we even if we freeze
part of the weights and relearn the others. I think
one nice thing about the make
sure we use algorithm is that
technically, it can work with
any method that falls under this offline
mixing schema. So if you're familiar
with things like reg mix or data mixing
laws, you could also just
this sort of meta procedure.
And the second question is, can you apply
this method iteratively? So
consider you split this existing
domains more and more, and, you
throw existing parts, and can
you achieve better results
than if you just split
in the first step and the full
computation. Can you explain
in what setting is it iterative? Yeah.
So for example, you have a really large
web and you want to split it into multiple
for recommendation from scratch instead of
and and the alternative would be
to to some weight on web first and
then split only first
part of web into separate domain. And
do, like, a computation on that. And then,
split again the existing part and and so and so
on.
I think we
yeah, I think we have some results in the paper
where we do this sort of like we can continue,
like, doing these sorts of, like, splitting and,
like, freezing and recomputing. And
it's like there's a lot of theory
on, like, when it works and when it doesn't work. So
I would recommend checking that out.
Thanks for the great talk. I have
a question about, like, what
so in the paper, you have, like, 1,000,000,000
parameter models as your target model size.
And then you get a bunch of proxy models. Do
you also have any sense of how would the proxy
model size scale with like, maybe
a 7,000,000,000 or a 70,000,000,000 model
Yeah.
You know, 15,000,000 is not gonna be
great for a 70,000,000,000 parameter model. I
think my guess is that
the ratio of proxy to target
is fixed. So I was looking at some other like
scaling law papers there's
like a paper called like a Hitchhiker's Guide
to Scaling Laws. And if you look at
some of their plots there, you kind of see this
sort of like fixed ratio,
phenomenon where it's like
yeah, like if 15,000,000
is good for 1,000,000,000, then 15,000,000,000
is good for a 100,000,000,000. So
that would be my hypothesis.
And I also have another question. I remember
seeing some other paper from AI too, which used,
like, this 30,000,000 model proxy
size. I think it's like the web organizer paper.
So what are done after you've got this result
or they just lucky and they found the
right proxy size? I think,
Web Organizer came before us
but they were kind of using a different setting. So
when I started this we just kind
of re reswept everything
to double check. Yeah. But
I think they also had some similar
experiments to look at the
the stability across proxy to target.
Thank you. Great job.
Hi. Thank you for the great talk. Patyush from
NVIDIA here. My
question is maybe related to, how
you chose, the domains
for omics? Because I imagine that hyperparameter
m has a lot to do with choosing
the number of proxies in,
the method. So I'm wondering if
for the datasets, does Olmec
recover domains or the partitions between
domains specifically for unstructured datasets, or
is that out of scope for this study?
So we were pretty much using
like fixed, domains.
I guess what we the procedure
of o mix isn't really
splitting new domains.
We use web organizer to do a
lot of the to determine
a lot of the domains. Largely. So,
you can think of that as like a
a stage in advance. Or like if you curate a
new dataset, you can split it
using web organizer, and then you can pass
it into homemix. Got it. I
I saw on the future works slide that that
might be a a potential direction in
terms of other stages of curation. Is that something else I'm
thinking about? I see. Okay. Yeah. We
weren't really the example we had
there was just like we ran the mix
the coefficients from the fit and
that kind of gives you a notion of
influence of each domain. And we kind of looked
and we were like, oh, some of these domains are really
they have they don't have that much data, but they're really
high influence. So then we just
like sample more from that domain. But we
haven't looked at like if we should change the partition
or anything like that.
Thank you. Yeah.
Hi. It's a very good clock.
And I have a question on, the validation
benchmark choosing. Because as
we know, if you increase, your math
ratios, you will
perform better in, like, math task.
And vice versa. So
I think it's very, it's highly,
related, and it's very important to
choose your validation suits
suite. And it will, highly,
determine your mixing ratio.
And I think so how to solve
this egg and chicken dilemma? Yeah.
Yeah. That's a great question. So
a few things we did there, we played around
with first like, weighted objectives.
So we kind of see we had actually
quite a bit of math tasks and so
we were like, okay, maybe we should down
weight the math tasks a bit.
And so that kind of helps, but
more broadly, I think of the data
mixing problem as like you
always need an objective to
optimize against so the first
question is just given some objective,
can you optimize that
well? And then a separate question
is, is that objective, like, meaningful?
So that's, like, the high level question. And then we also
did add explore some, Pareto
constraints. So in the
mixture optimization, we added
some constraint to be like,
need to ensure that this mix does
not perform more
worse than epsilon compared to the
natural distribution on any task
So that kind of helps you steer it to
be like a generally good model. So
there's there's a lot of ways to do this. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Thank you. Go. Awesome.
Okay. So, let's thank, Mei
again.
Okay. So, the next
oral presentation is by Fazil
from Oxford. To talk about
the capability frontier, the benchmarks
miss 28% of the model performance.
Let's welcome Fazil.
Good morning, everyone. Thanks so
much for being here. I hope you're having a
nice conference.
Can you hear me at the back?
Great. Okay. So
So this is, work that
we've done that have done at Marshen. The first author
is Brad Fowler, who couldn't be here today so
I'm presenting on behalf of Brad.
And So I wanted to start by giving
you headline result.
As the title of the talk. So you don't have
to wait for it for the next ten
minutes or so. Also so then you can focus
on the rest of the talk. So
yeah. As the headline suggests,
benchmark misses 82%
of model performance. So and
perhaps this is not in some hypothetical future,
is with, you know, models that are sitting on Hacking Face
Library today.
So for the rest of the talk, I wanted to talk
about how we measure this
and why the best of our knowledge, nobody
has measured it correctly until now.
And what this changes, if you take, this
result seriously. And
perhaps one reason we care about these sort of problems
is that you know, LLM usage
are increasing every day. So if
you want to figure out which model is best
for the sort of questions you have in mind,
it's probably best, is is a good question
to ponder over. So
yeah. So,
perhaps if you then think about why
different models went on different
questions, then we can figure out that
if you take a really widely
used, benchmark like
MLMU, medical, you can
see that different models actually perform
massively differently on on different subset
of this this benchmark.
So in particular,
GPT-four might win on medical
you know, genetics and anatomy,
Matt Pal might win on professional medicine and
on college medicine. Know, these are the
same domains and same benchmarks, just different
sub domains. So, perhaps
you get these sort of different winners.
Maybe one thing that is worth flagging is that
this is this is an unusual or some cherry
picked results. But we see this pattern
across every benchmark we looked at. And
every model that kind of shapes the competence.
So it's not necessarily a
a level competence, but rather the shape
that, that is different from one model to
the next.
So you might think, uh-huh. Yeah. Well, this
is easy. You can just build an Oracle
and, you know, you can beat, you can beat this.
So this might be an
obvious, thought, if models specialize in
this particular way, then something that
could pick the right model per question
for example, an article could potentially
beat, them all individually.
And not by a small amount. You know, the headroom
in every benchmark
is basically the room for you to win.
However, the standard evaluation never really
measures it because standard evaluation runs
model in isolation and reports one number per
model. And, you know, perhaps you're
measuring the wrong unit.
Well, we are meant to actually measure, models
when what people actually
deploy in real world settings.
So So what is the problem with
creating such oracle allows you to
measure these performances?
Great. So there are two opposing biases.
The first one is
perhaps just we compute the
oracle and you pick the model
the best model per question and you average
it across all the runs.
Now, this isn't something new, people have
done this in the past. For
example, you might be familiar with Router Bench, RouterLM
and many others.
They all performed some form of
these aggregation.
The problem here is more subtle than than what
it looks. There are actually two
biases pulling against each other. Single
model benchmarks understates
because the specialization we just
talked about but also naive oracles
in themselves overestimates.
The reason that's poorly understood in the routing literature
even if you have been looking
at it for a while.
So, on one hand, one
number that is reported as too low
and we fix that, that produces too much of a
high number and until you
handle both, you don't actually know what the
real capability at the frontier of the ecosystem
is. So in some sense,
this is the gap we are trying to address in this in this paper.
So
why might, what does the
capability might look like? So, here
object we are trying to measure basically that
frontier capability. So in some sense, the
gray dots are individual
elements at default settings
each one points in quality cost
space, Some are cheaper and weak, some
are more expensive and strong,
and some, you know, kind of get stuck in the middle.
And perhaps the the red curve
what we call the capabilities frontier. So
if you optimize both of these things, this
is what you might get. So
the best quality, you know, that you can achieve at
any given budget. And
if you were routing optimally across models,
and across multiple, you know,
generations across different,
temperature per query, this
is this is essentially what my what you might
get. So notice somehow
this is well above the
single model frontier. So
this is the gap that, you know, you can't really
put a single number on. And for any
cost you pick, the quality you're leaving,
there's there's some quality you're leaving on the table.
So for any quality target
you pick, there is a cheaper way to achieve it.
And we go in some details on how you might do this
in in the paper. Now let's
look at why some naive oracles
might might overstate.
So I think there is a problem with the clicker.
So maybe we can spend a little
bit of time on why
the naive oracles overstated this problem.
And I think this is perhaps maybe
one of the main issues that is poorly understood
in the in the literature.
This is because
if you think about the intuition here,
if you run each model 10
times on each prompt, you compute
an average accuracy per model.
Then for each prompt, you pick the model
with the highest, you know, samples
sample average, and you call it, you know, the oracle.
Perhaps this sounds very reasonable.
However, the problem is that when you take a
maximum over you know, there's noisy
estimates, you pick the model
that's actually best at on that prompt.
So you preferentially
pick the model whose 10 samples just somehow
got lucky on those prompts as opposed to the
model that might actually be better.
So the lucky model in some
sense looks like the winner even when
there are true performance is
maybe not as good as what is what is reported.
So this is the
oracle upper bound that you have seen in a bunch
of previous literature.
So this effect is perhaps not new.
If you if you look at history, you know,
the petroleum industry run
into similar issues, and, you know,
they referred to this as the optimizers
curves in 2006. So, somehow
shows up in different domains and different literature
where you take, you know, marks
over some noisy settings you run into this
issue. So in some sense,
we are trying to see whether
this problem also persists in the
LAM routing space. And what's what the
magnitude is, larger than what you'd expect
and how we can fix for it.
So So
how do you, device the frontier estimation?
So we use two particular debiasing
methods. One is
extrapolation, where we
measure the bias decay as you add more and
more samples and we fit that, you know, until we fit
the limit. The second is
a probabilistic graphical model that
estimates each model's, true accuracy
probability of a query type.
The two methods are, you know,
independent but they make different,
assessments of, and assumptions about what is
what they try to use in in terms of
the mechanistic explanation.
Know, they may actually agree with each other with
infractions of a percent but
the agreement is, you know, is what lets us
measure results
of the two the two approaches.
Some sense, if they disagree, then, you know, we would have a
we would have a problem.
So before I show you some of the
results, this is, maybe
what sort of models and what sort of benchmarks and
how many queries per per
queries we look at. So, you know,
that 21 models these are
chosen based on what is
commonly used, what's reported in
other papers, across 16 different benchmarks
and ten ten different prompts.
So at a matched
cost, you
for the same data, for the same question,
We are trying to see
when you're spending no more than the best single
model for on each benchmark, the
device frontier reduces error rates
about 54% on average.
The headline results. So if you
look at human eval
CPP or GP, g p two a
diamond, and many other
benchmarks, you can see this reduction
in error about on about 8080%.
So, the reason I
want you to take the thing that I
would like to take you off from this is that the
spread is that the spread correlates
between heterogeneous benchmarks
which I guess
allows us to split the sort
of issues that we see into two, two devices
that I mentioned earlier.
So at much quality,
we see that cost can drop
to up to six x. So
if you are given the same data and the same question,
and you want to hold the quality,
fixed, you know, any state
of the art single model number how
cheap can you get? Like what's the best results
the lowest cost you can possibly get? So
we find that you can actually get 85%
cheaper on average You know, that's about
a sixth of the price for the same accuracy.
This is often you know,
perhaps the slide of the result that
would matter most for those of you who are in industry
and who who care about models
in production. So
in some sense, what most people are
paying right now is the cost of choosing
one model committing to it as opposed
to experimenting with a bunch of models.
You know, the the human knowledge here is maybe,
you have a bunch of different friends,
if you always go to a friend for
advice and you have to buy them a coffee,
and they're not the best at giving you advice on
every then, you know,
you have wasted some money on on the coffee. So
I can you do?
So if you go one step further and add a
verifier at inference time, try
and try to, you know, generate multiple generations,
and you keep the best one, know, you can
actually, climb up the amounts of
error you can reduce. And again, this is
about 82%. So
thus headline result that I was just I
was just talking about. So
but there is obviously some caveats here. Right? This,
you know, assumes a perfect free verifier,
and no real verifier is either
perfect nor nor free. So there
is somewhat of an upper bound on what what
is really attainable here.
So you know, it's not really yet
at the scale of deployable systems, maybe
perhaps what this tells you even at
the level of imperfect verifiers
in domains where verification is cheap,
example, anything that you have ground truth
cogeneration, math, etcetera, you can
capture a lot of a lot of these, these
results. So perhaps this is
also an active area of research that you're
interested in.
So, in
some sense, what we care about here is,
how can you get
given the the issues that we discussed,
how can you get, more of the gains?
So the thing I want
you I I wanted to take away from
here is that in some sense, we need to
measure systems as opposed to models.
Because these models are not static objects
that they will just perform themselves.
But they are, you know, part of a much bigger
of a much bigger system that we care about.
So So obviously, this
changes the way we think about evaluations.
Deployment, and research. I'd be very interested
in talking to people about each of these
specifically about how do you go and
extract the true capabilities of this model such
that prior to seeing the query, you have
an understanding of the quality and cost
ratio might be.
So So
I want to leave you with this
perhaps provocative and hot claim.
In some sense, maybe we need to move away from
measuring models and we need
to start measuring systems. And I
think the capabilities are already there.
And maybe in some sense the next
few years of the progress will
come from trying to unveil and
recover these capabilities. Thanks so much
for your time and happy to take questions.
Thanks. Are are there any
questions?
Okay. So if there are no questions,
then since we are already off the
time, yeah, so, you can talk to
offline. Yeah. Thank you so much.
Thank you so let's thanks, Fado again.
Yeah. So, now let's move to
our the last
oral presentation in the morning session.
Yeah. So, so
this talks will be given by,
on memorization and
data selection. This is a
a Zipwhip paper got the best
paper word for our workshop,
which is the only one among the
168 submissions.
Yeah.
So, let's welcome, Kunal.
Alright. Thank you. Yeah.
So I'll be talking about some joint work with
these, amazing collaborators.
Who is, normally at Ten US
and was an intern at Apple. When
she did this work. And with Ali Feldman,
who is a colleague at Apple.
Okay. So guess today we'll
be asking questions about memorization
in in language models,
I normally work on privacy. So normally,
you will be hearing me talking about
how to prevent memorization in models.
But today is different. Today, we'll instead
be asking how do we get the models
to memorize as well as they can.
The motivation for this can be multiple
there are settings where we want
the model to memorize some kind of factual information.
So for example, we may we may
want the model to learn, to be able to
answer the question when did Neil Armstrong
set foot on the moon?
Or we may be able we may want the model
to be able to
to take a picture and tell you where this
picture was taken. If this is a famous landmark.
Guess in this talk, we'll be focusing on,
having this memorization be part of the parametric
memory of the model. So all of
this information, we want it to be present
in the parameters of the model.
We are not thinking about having,
rag or any other,
additional access.
For the model. We're really asking
if I want to train a model or fine tune
a model, and I want the parameters of the
model to memorize
some set of facts. How best can
we do that?
Okay. So there is already evidence. There's,
previous work showing that
that our models today are not very good
at this. So especially when you look
at tail facts, facts that don't
occur too many times in the corpus,
our models are not very good at being able
to, to give this information,
to to retrieve
factual information from these models.
And I guess this work also kind of
some extrapolation and, suggested that
if we really wanted to memorize
all the factual information in Wikipedia,
we would need a model which has some
really, really absurd size, completely unreasonable. So
just by scaling things as we are
we have today, we can't even memorize,
all the facts on Wikipedia.
So this begs the question. So I guess
is this something intrinsic? Is this something
that really the capacity of the
model is not large enough? Or perhaps
a retrieval process is not good enough?
Or is this something we can hope to address,
by better approaches to training or data selection?
So that's what we are going to do today.
We'll take some steps in this direction.
To start with, we'll look at kind
of synthetic setup. So we'll first
try to understand the capacity of
these models in an idealized
setting. Where we can properly define what
capacity means, what memorization
means, and we can also very carefully
and reliably
measure all of these things.
And then we'll tweak these conditions. We'll see how
tweaking things, in the
distribution, in this idealized setting
changes things.
This will
motivate our algorithms or
new heuristics to, for dataset
selection as we'll see in a few minutes.
And finally, we'll take
these algorithms and then apply them to real world
world data. And show
that they continue to work there.
Okay. So let's get going. So we'll start
with a synthetic data distribution.
Meaning that we'll basically make up facts.
So these facts are kind
of analogous to names
followed by phone numbers or celebrity
names followed by their
their birthdays.
In our setup, we
basically take random identifiers
followed by a random sequence of digits which correspond to
their their phone
number perhaps. And I guess
the nice thing about this is because we pick this randomly,
we know this stuff is not in the
pre training data. We know how much entropy
it has. This is
something we can control as an all.
So
So that gives us a set of facts that
we are trying to memorize. Given
the facts, we can define a training data
distribution, by
by taking samples from this set of facts.
Right? So I guess the simplest thing to do would be to take
a uniform distribution of our facts.
So my training dataset just contains
each of those facts that
I'm trying to memorize the same number of times
or right?
Oops.
Good. So I guess in this model, we can actually study
what happens. People have studied models like this
before and shown empirically that
models typically have, like,
two bits per parameter capacity.
And this is what our experiments show as well for
our model.
We can also prove theorems about this setting. So
as you would expect, the number of facts you
can memorize does grow linearly with the number
of parameters you have. It grows inversely
with the, amount of
entropy in each, in each fact.
But, typically, if we are trying
to understand fact accuracy,
if I ask for somebody's phone number and you get
half of the digits right, that's not particularly
useful. Right? So it's not just about
the entropy or entropy
reduction, It's really about an
all or nothing accuracy measure. We
want to make sure that
for any of these queries,
you give me the correct answer. If you get half the digits
right, that doesn't count for anything.
So that motivates us to,
measuring this all or nothing version
of the problem.
Where you get credit for
correctly outputting the fact that
we are talking about.
And here's what happens when you train on the uniform
distribution. As you give the model more and
more facts, it can memorize more and more
facts. Until at some point,
which is roughly the
capacity limit, for this process,
it stops memorizing anything at all.
Effectively, what's happening in the model is that it's
memorizing half of the information in
each of the facts. Or a small
fraction, but because
we care about fact accuracy,
fact retrieval, we get see
this precipitous drop on the left hand
side.
When you give it a power law distribution,
this something interesting that happens. So the model
still memorizes something. I
guess it makes sense that stuff that the model
sees more often. It
will still memorize
but you also see a nontrivial
drop in the capacity of the model.
So those points in the middle that you
see there those are all
they're all of those settings are cases where the
number of facts we are giving the model
are within the capacity of the model.
If we had given those same facts in
a uniform distribution, the model would have memorized
it. But we see this reduction
in capacity.
So
So I guess these findings
kind of motivate our, our heuristic
at a high level, what we want to do if you give me a power
law distribution is firstly,
if you have, more facts than there
is capacity in the model, you should
just leave out the facts that the
model is not going to memorize anyway.
There's no point in cramming more because if you
cram more, the model learns.
Less.
And second, as we saw in the power
log graph, if you
if the data distribution has some skew, it
makes it harder for the model to learn.
And therefore, we want to flatten the distribution
flatten the head of the distribution.
So ideally, what we want is an
data selection which looks like this.
You cut off the tail of the distribution,
and you flatten the head. You make
you try to achieve roughly uniform
distribution over just the right number of facts.
And then we can, of course, do this in the synthetic data
setting when we actually control
the data distribution. We can actually make this change, but
that's not very useful. If you want to really deploy
this in the real world,
so what we show in this work is
that there is a simple proxy that we can use
for the frequency of the items.
Which is the loss. So
if we measure the loss
on the fact tokens,
after, say, a small number of iterations.
For tokens in the tail, the
fact loss is high because they haven't been memorized at all.
For tokens in the head, the fact loss
is the the loss on
those tokens is, is lower because
the model has memorized them already to some
extent. So after doing one epoch,
we can use,
the current loss do the selection.
We basically choose a threshold for facts
which are above that threshold. We think of those
as facts in the tail. We just drop
those facts completely from the
training set.
And for facts that whose loss is below
the threshold, we keep them with probability proportional
to the loss. Lower loss means we have a
lower probability of keeping them because
they are likely in the head already.
So and in practice,
this does leak to significantly better
memorization. So on these synthetic
datasets, our algorithm
kind of improves the capacity. It doesn't drop.
As you see on the left. And on the right, you
see when we have a a power law distribution,
the capacity increases significantly.
So this is this is great. So we have a training
method which is just based on loss.
Is something you can implement without trying
to learn anything about the data distribution.
And it gives us significantly better memorization.
But in this current form, this model still needs
a couple of things. So first, it needs fact
boundaries. I guess to be able
to compute the laws on effect,
I need to know where the fact begins and
ends. And while I can do
that for synthetic data, for real data, this may be
harder. Thankfully,
recent work has shown that you can
actually annotate
data using using language models.
To to define fact boundaries around
facts. So I guess this worked by Joe Vital,
released this dataset where they just took Wikipedia
and used an LLM to, to annotate
some of the sentences as facts.
With clear boundaries. So that's what
we use in our, real world experiments.
We need to modify the selection method
a little bit because now we have both fact tokens
and non fact tokens. The non fact
tokens, we want to leave them as is.
For the fact tokens, we want to essentially
apply our method, which is what we do.
The other thing our method needs to know is how
much capacity there is, and, how
much entropy there is in each
each fact. This is something that we don't
really know because,
we don't really know how much entropy each fact
has. So we just tune
this parameter tau, to,
to figure out what the best
value is.
So we did this on this real world dataset
from Wikipedia. Here are some results.
Our selection method, if you apply it,
it significantly improves the
fact accuracy, the number of facts that the model
can memorize. So
I guess, you can see
this plot in two ways. You can either think of
this as we're getting 30%
more facts
for the same capacity
or I guess maybe a more flattering way to think of
this is if you train on the full
dataset, you would need a 10 times larger dataset
10 times larger model to memorize
the same number of facts.
So with our selection, we can
get the same amount of fact memorization with
the 10 times smaller model.
Compared to training. The full
dataset. Now you might worry
that, we are distorting the data the training
data distribution that may hurt accuracy
on other tasks on language understanding.
So we did some ablation
studies here and we see that
the accuracy on various, natural
language understanding task is essentially unaffected.
By our selection method.
Get similar results for fine tuning on
a semi synthetic authors
and, paper
titles, dataset.
Once again, we can while full
dataset training just
does not do very well,
our method consistently,
improves over,
over the original model. Without affecting
the general capability.
Okay. So that's all I'll have time to tell about
today. The paper has more theory, a lot
more experiments and ablations. And
it's on the archive, so have a look.
Let me just conclude by summarizing. So
what I so basically, we showed
that in synthetic simple settings,
memorization in models is really
adversely impacted by a,
having too many effects, that
we are asking the model to memorize,
And b, just the distribution of those
facts actually also impacts the
memorization. We proposed
a simple data selection scheme, based
on these observations,
and we show how we can implement the scheme based
on loss alone.
And we showed that it worked well on,
synthetic as well as real data sets.
I think there's a lot more to be done here. I
think of facts as sort of the
simplest setting for dataset selection where
we can really understand what
it
it really isolate the amount of information
in each, data point.
I would hope that we can kind of do similar investigations
for, more for
other tasks where there's some structured learning happening
and perhaps similar phenomena
must occur For example, maybe
your model is trying to learn many different
simple models, simple linear regressions.
If there's a
if the distribution over the amount of data
you have for each is not uniform,
would imagine similar
similar degradations happen. So I think there's a lot
more to be done here. I'll stop here. Thank
you.
Hello. I have two questions. The
first one is have you, looked into
the data that you have like, selected
out? And did you know, like,
any takeaways on what kind of data would
be likely to be selected out?
And the other question is, do you have
any any other following
up method to deal with these facts? So,
like, how to remember them or
yeah. Things like that.
Sorry. Could you repeat the second question? Yeah. The
second one is is, since you have selected out
some facts from what you want to train the
model, so what do you want to do with
these facts if yeah. Sure.
So great question. So I think for the
first question, we do
have
we at least in the synthetic setting.
Kind of,
looked at the actual,
probability of being selected.
And our method based on loss actually does
correspond very well to the
idealized method where we keep the head and throw away the
tail. So essentially, what
the facts we are throwing away are the facts which
have low frequency in the training dataset.
So hopefully, these are facts that are
less important. If we had to throw away some, these are
the ones you would want to throw out.
It's a good question what we would want to do with them.
I guess if you have a hybrid
setup where you do rag or something on some
datasets,
on some queries. You could throw
them into the rack.
But I think even in the case where you have enough
capacity to memorize everything, I think this
downscaling the head seems to help a
lot, and I think that's you should do anyway.
Okay. Thank you.
Hi. Thank you for the great talk.
You mentioned that you had an empirical
discovery that you can
store two bits of information per
per parameter in the model.
I have two questions about that. The first one
is, do you have an intuition for why it's two
beats?
No. Okay. I guess, I should clarify this
two bits has come from previous work.
Couple of previous papers which have observed
these two bits.
Yeah. I don't know why two bits, I
guess. Okay. And the second one is
do you have any, ideas on how we
can increase that, rate limit?
Of two bits that that we could increase
somehow? Question.
That's a very good
question. I I
don't. I mean, I would say like, personally,
I think the fact that you can actually
get to constant number of bits per parameter
is already fairly surprising.
I wouldn't expect that, you
can go much further
yeah. So I think, really, we need to
sort of have methods which sort of control
what bits of the information what bits
of information the model memorizes
Yeah. Okay. Thank you.
Thanks for the great talk. I have more
general question.
Do you have a sense of how much
how useful is memorization for generalization
or at which point
I does model start generalizing after
memorizing? You have a general text
there?
I don't so I guess my colleague, Vitali, has done
some work on this back in the day
where he showed that
there are settings if you have if you're
if the things you are trying to learn
actually have a power law distribution,
then memorization is really necessary for
generalization.
The mental picture I have is of which
there's no evidence, is that the model starts
memorizing things and then as it sees
more and more of similar objects,
it tries to generalize
rather than memorize individuals.
I guess we have some evidence of this. We
have some theoretical work that kind of
says that, this is the
this is what must happen,
in any model?
But I think we need to do more work in trying to understand
the mechanics of how this is happening in
in real models. Yeah.
Thanks, Ganahl. Great talk. I was wondering
if you get us got us an answer to explore
how robust the method is to the
segmentation of the facts that you're
getting from the model. And
second question, like, some facts
can be simple, but then you can also have
compositional facts that can
be more tricky to memorize and might
appear very, less frequently. So
do the same type of takeaways, would you expect
them to hold for compositional,
facts as well? So it's a good question.
So I guess we didn't so I mean,
I think the the annotations
we used were LLM generated, so they
would almost certainly have errors.
We did not quite explore, how
robust our method is, but I would expect
it's, reasonably
robust in the sense that guess, if you
are selecting a subset to memorize,
as long as the subset is reasonably
as a reasonable approximation to the head of the
distribution, you're doing better
than what you would otherwise.
I would say another thing that we are currently ignoring
maybe we even get to compositional knowledge
is like, theoretical
our the
relationship between frequency and loss
holds if all all facts have
the same amount of entropy. But real world
facts will have different amounts of entropy. So I think one
thing that seems very natural to try to do
is to, perhaps use another
model to figure out how much entropy each fact has
and take that into account. When,
doing the selection,
and we did not look into composition. I think that's,
definitely something we need to look at.
Thanks, Kunal, for the great talk. Can
I ask a little bit more on the part that
we see, like, no performance
harm on the other task?
What's the intuition there? Did we do anything
special? Can understand that our
selection process kind of removed
some redundant fact But are these
data also redundant for other tasks?
Or the general capability or or
what's the intuition there?
Yeah. So I guess that's our intuition that we are
kind of selecting a small number of
things as facts. And if we fudge with the
facts, then that
there isn't sort of a lot of natural
language understanding that's lost when we
mess with that?
I could imagine there's very specific kinds
of
general information that,
that may be lost when you do something like this.
But yeah. I guess. So that's why we did this experiment
to actually evaluate how much we lose. We
did have to, re weigh things.
So I guess if we are sub selecting the
facts, but
not subset selecting the non facts,
you end up with less weight on the facts total.
So we had to rescale to
get the same amount of weight as before.
But other than that, we did not make any change. Yeah.
Yeah. I see. Thanks. I may have
missed it. What's the percentage of data we
have select out? So
I think that's a hyperparameter we tune. Typically,
in the experiments, I showed, it was, like,
between 1020%. That we
keep. And we throw out the rest.
Okay. Thanks.
Okay. Let's thank,
Kungel again.
The first poster session, starts now.
Everyone. Could you
please take a seat? Let's start
our afternoon session. We have
very exciting program
in the afternoon. And
if you want more time for poster session, we do
have a second poster session. Like, we have
a lot of breaks, a lot of interaction time.
Don't worry about that. For now,
could you all take a seat?
And for if you have friends outside,
like, hanging around,
you can tell them that we are starting our
afternoon session.
Folks, could you all sit down at this
point? Let's start our
afternoon session.
Okay. Let's start our exciting
afternoon session Juan, do you want
to come on stage and yeah.
So to start our afternoon,
we have one exciting
keynote talk. From Juan
Carlos Nabors. And,
Juan Carlos Nabuls is research
director at Salesforce and,
adjunct adjunct professor of computer science
at Stanford. He's also
co director of the Stanford Vision and
Learning Lab. His research
spans computer vision, machine learning, multimodal
AI, and autonomous agents. Previously,
he had research leadership roles at the
Stanford Toyota Center for AI Research and Stanford
AI Lab. And was also an
associate professor at University
Del Norte in Colombia. He earned
his engineering degree from University Darnati.
He's not
his master from UIUC and his PhD
from Princeton. He has published over
100 papers in top venues,
serves in leadership roles for major
Vision conferences and, IEEE
Tami, and receive orders including
the Google faculty
research, Microsoft research faculty Fellowship, and
Fulbright Fellowship. It's really a
honor to have professor
Juan Carlos Naples here in
Latin America. I guess you are are
it's also close to home. Yeah. Happy to
give a talk here close to your home
Okay. Let's welcome
Alright. Well, thank you very much everybody for coming.
I know it's right after lunch and
it's Sunday so you're making an effort to be
here and I'm happy to be here to share
some of our work. So thank you to organizers for giving the
chance to to do that.
So I wanted to talk about today
is agentic ambient intelligence
and a little bit of background, there's
a lot of excitement these days
around AI agents specially
designed for the digital world. We can
see them in coding assistance, we see them in computer
use agents, and even frameworks like
open cloud are creating a lot of interesting,
discussions around the world. But we
must remember that our most
meaningful activities still happen in person.
In the physical world. In fact, we're here today
in Brazil attending
this conference as an example of that.
So that's the reason why I'm
thinking about our research work and how it
relates to the idea of agentic ambient
intelligence. Building AI technology
that can augment and super power our
physical in person activities.
And to illustrate this vision, I want to show
two examples. First,
think about wearable smart glasses.
Imagine this user that's assembling
a complex dresser, and we
want to move beyond glasses that simply
record what's happening and rather
we want agents that understand the
task so deeply that they can
provide real time feedback and guidance
to to the user.
Second, think of, high stress
residential move where this human,
has a robot and he's acting
as a director deciding what to keep,
what to donate, what to pack. While
the robot acts as an expert assistance
that is doing all the
boring tedious labor work of of packing.
So for that, the robot needs to understand
ambiguous commands to understand
environmental context, to be
able to do that effectively. So to achieve this
type of vision, we need to bridge
a gap between what
we can do in digital reasoning,
and physical action. So today, I
wanna cover four core capabilities
that, we think are required to make this,
a reality. So let me start with
a more specific example. Imagine
that our smart glass user
is assembling this drawer, and
they point a finger at a specific board
on the floor. And they may ask, should this
board be installed horizontally like the
one just finished?
Or maybe in the case of the robot,
the the mover asks, the robot, can
you wrap up wrap this cup?
Like, the around and the ones I washed five minutes
ago? So
that brings us to our first capability that I'll
talk about today which is about the ability
of vision language models to answer
questions with space
time preferences. So
if we look at current models, they actually fail at
this. They struggle with this fine grained
special to polar reasoning especially
when the queries themselves
like this one, rely on time based
event references for temporal anchoring
or gesture cues for spatial anchoring.
So why is this happening?
Perhaps one of the issues as we see today in
in most foundation models is that
potentially there is not enough data in the training to capture
this type of of capability.
So we try to look at that and try to bridge
that gap by introducing this framework which we
call Strefer, It's a data
generation engine that automatically synthesizes
data training data for these particular scenarios.
So idea is that by learning with
this automatically generated data,
then we can enable new
critical capabilities. So I'm gonna show you a couple.
So here's an example. We can using this
data, we generate automatically. We can make
models learn to interpret queries
where a user is pointing at an entity.
For example, here, the user points at a person
in the video and may ask something like,
could you describe his action?
And in the prompt, the model not only
receives the question, but also receives
a mask that's derived from the pointing gesture
to help it help the model clarify
who he is.
So So so using this data we
we created, we can get the models to answer
this this type of question. So this is
spatial referencing. But another interesting
capability is that of temporal references. So
here, we can ask questions such
as what is happening to that boy
wearing glasses from three seconds to nine seconds.
So again, temporarily, pointing
at certain parts of the video.
And now that even the this boy wearing
glasses is not visible during that time span,
of the video. So we with this
data generation pipeline, we can also generate
these type of negative questions
asking about identities that aren't
even there in that portion of the video.
And this is just to make sure that the model isn't
just guessing or hallucinating information or taking
any shortcuts, but really truly
understanding the video's timeline.
But of course, we can combine these two types of referencing.
Right? We can ask models to
or we can also hopefully enable models to interpret
this more complex questions
that involve both mask
and timestamp preferences.
So here's here for example, we we can
ask what did he do, what in seconds, and the models
hopefully get able to to answer that type of questions.
So of course, the key problem is how do we generate
this type data? And
and here's the full straightforward data generation pipeline.
It's a complex pipeline, but I would say
before talking about how it works is that
this idea of I want to get a new
capability my models are not good at it,
So how can I reuse what I already
can do to generate data so I can
train my model to get to that view capability?
So this is what we're trying to do here.
And we orchestrate this,
multiple models that have simpler
complementary strengths, and in
our implementation, we focus just on
using open models to achieve
this. So here's how
level how it works. Given an input video,
we first use a video LLM to describe
the active subjects in the video like
the girl in a white dress, and then
use an NLLM to describe
to to parse this into noun
phrases and and generalized nouns.
Which then we can feed into a novel module
that produces masculine. These are
tracked object segmentation masks So, this
give us a way to follow the entities throughout
the the video sequence.
So that's one way to generate the special
references and then on the other hand, we
have the temporal references which
which we can generate by
dividing the video into short clips, and
then using a video alarm to describe
the short clips especially
focusing on behavior style
descriptions for all the entities that
we had discovered in the upper portion.
And finally, now we have this set of temporally
dense transcripts for all the clips
in the video and all the entities with
tracks so we can use that to generate
instruction style question answer in pairs.
Okay? So we can run this and because it's fully automatic,
we can do this at scale. So here's an
example of what we can obtain.
Where we have input videos, we run through
our software pipeline, can generate
this type of instructions which
include a segmentation mask and a question,
using this space and temporal references
together with the response that we need the model to produce.
Okay? So as I said, because this is completely automatic,
we can scale it up. And in fact,
using this pipeline, we generated nearly a million
data samples from just over
4,000 source videos
from from the next QA dataset. So
so now we have this large data. What can we use this
to train a model? Again, state models are
to get them to do new things. Many times,
we need to to train them with large amount of
data, so we did that and we trained
the split three Strecker model,
which is an enhanced version of our own
Blip three video model And
we have some results here but I just wanna
say that we show that by using this
Strephro synthesized data,
we can boost performance of the models, especially
in these type of questions that have
special references, important references and so
on. So I think the key here is that
we can achieve these gains
by designing carefully designing the synthetically
synthetic generation of data
in a in a full automatic way without the need of this costly
human annotation or a massive new
video collection which is always expensive.
So, yeah. So in summary I guess up
to this part, we have this fully scalable,
system for generating data
and we focus really on getting better at
this space time preferences questions
and we introduce, particularly
a novel component
about generating this mask
references. Okay.
So that's what we have talked about, Strecker
getting these models to answer space time references.
But once we get these agents to see and
understand when and what is happening,
we we can have them to face, more complex
challenges. For example,
let's raise the bar a little bit in these two scenarios
we are talking about. Let's
say that, our smart glasses user is
securing a fastener
into a particle board and suddenly they hear
a sharp crack They may freeze,
they may be worried that have damaged the
wood. So they look at the manual
that is on this, structural manual that
is on the floor and the user may ask, I just
heard this loud cracking sound while I was tightening
this lock. Can you look at the
torque warning in the manual there? Did I
just split the wood or is that the
sound of the fastener locking into place? What
what's going on? And
in the case of the robot, maybe the robot is packing
this vintage electronics and has this
wooden clock and it's moving
it around and it starts rattling, so it hears
all those noises. And this
three d sensor is captured, and there's some fracture on the
base of the clock. And and the camera
sees a sticker about warning to to
handle carefully. So in this
case is what we need is to the AI model
to process these multiple modalities, right? The
the video, the images, the audio,
the three d scans, and the agent needs to
decide somehow where from
all these signals is the answer to my
question. That takes us
to, to our next core
capability which is about cross model
reasoning. And again, the role this
real world model system real world systems
are constantly flooded with
multiple sensory inputs before the models can
reason, they really need to identify the
the sensor source that can hold
the specific answer to the query.
So the question is how can we evaluate
this type of capability? What are we
in this in this, in this
setting? So so to do
that, of course, we have to think about benchmarking
and, to unfortunately, there is
no benchmarking for this cross model type
of task. So we to
understand, we introduced this Contra four
benchmark. And the core task here is simple again.
We but it's demanding. We want
given these inputs from multiple
modalities and a text query,
we need the model to decide which modality
best matches or best
corresponds to that query. So an example
here, the model needs to select which scene is
more likely to show a vehicle accident
and it gets these four options, a
three d scan, a sound, an image, and a video.
So of course, the primary challenge
building this type of benchmark is that this
truly aligned multimodal data
is incredibly scarce. And
it's very difficult to collect and and
very costly to annotate. So
so that's the the big challenge and I think
our key insight here is that
can we reuse existing
single modality benchmarks, by
using this language as a
as a connect connection
layer between the modalities.
So and and be able to find related data
points across disparate benchmarks
and sensors. So that's the idea.
And again, we build this dataset
by orchestrating and automating a pipeline
with multiple models that are working together to
to get us to to this type of data.
And, again, our idea is to reuse
the simple single modality bench
are already out there. So for example, we
have this three d data with captions and we
have image data with captions.
And we have, sound data
with captions and so on. So now,
we can operate the entire pipeline just based
on the captions.
And, that's what we do. So we start forming this
forming these topples of two four modalities
by doing sampling. And this sampling
we can do, let's say, randomly by selecting
samples from different datasets or we
can do similarity based sampling so that we
can really find those very closely related
samples and make the questions harder.
So that takes us to the next step,
which is to use these captions that we
have selected in the topples to generate questions
And, again, we use an LLM to do
the the question generation and,
then we also use another one another
one to generate answers with the detailed
explanations, making sure the answers are correctly
grounded into the metadata. And also
making sure that the questions
can only be answered by understanding the
modalities, not just simply by using language.
But okay, so this is great so far, but of course,
one of the key issues is how do you make sure this data
is of co quality so we have
this final step, which is about,
validation. So to guarantee
this human level quality, we use an ensemble
of models to check for round trip
consistency. And we only
keep samples that pass
the strictest filters based on various
levels of agreement.
Okay? So again, now we have a data generation
pipeline that we can scale.
And this results in a large dataset. We have
a 174,000
automatically generated training samples and we
have a set of about 2,000 samples that
are manually curated
and verified to make sure they
are of good quality. And what we find
actually is this last step I was showing about
filtering and agreement between different models is very important.
And when we start
by just using the simplest agreement method,
we see that human accuracy
is around 50%, which means there is a lot
of noise in the data. But as we get this
agreement across multiple models, we can push
that accuracy up to 83%.
So it shows that by using this multiple,
experts or models, you can
push up the the quality quite quite a
bit. Alright. Great. Now now we have a dataset,
we have a benchmark, so we can try to see how
models work. And in fact, there are
not that many models that are able to take in
this large set of modalities. Right? Input
of video, three three disc cans,
videos, images. So we
found every model we could find, that
do that and we tried to evaluate how well they
work on this. And we find that
human per the model performance is,
or the model performance is significantly lower
than human performance. And
so that means the models really
least. We
also see that the number of modalities
is inversely correlated to performance.
So when the questions have more than one modality
in the or the answers cover
more than two modalities, they tend to
be harder to answer for questions. So you see here
that questions were four four type
of modality in the answer, are
all more difficult than ones that only
have two. And
finally, because we also have training data, we try
fine tuning models and see whether that helps.
And, yes, there are some improvements, that
you can gain by by doing training.
And I guess one interesting observation here is
that better data quality, so the data that's
been filtered with more strict, filters
they trying to get
to better performance quicker, so
so, you know, you get a little bit faster performance
with better data. So but clearly,
there's still a lot to do for these models to get good
at dealing with this multiple modalities I
think. Okay. So in summary,
we introduced this new task. We call
constructed a a dataset, a benchmark, and
we showed that current models are still not
up to this task yet. That's
what we have been doing, trying to push for
this idea of
fusing knowledge from different
modalities and this task of cross modal reasoning.
But again, let's let's push the bar a
bit up again for these
two characters here.
Our agents are going into the real world,
they just won't just only be looking at ten
second clips, they will need to listen over
hours of video. An example
of the smart glasses, this user has been assembling
this drawer for forty five minutes and
then realizes that, maybe there's
a there's a wooden dowel leftover
after the assembly. So they may ask, hey, I have this
extra dowel. Can you scan the last hour
of video and tell me exactly what step did I
miss? Or in the case of robotics,
after six hour hours of packing,
the human realizes that they have lost, their
keys and they can say, hey, Robert,
can you scan your memory from the last
six hours and find where did I set my
keys down? While we were back in the kitchen.
So, that set us to our next capability
which is about reasoning over long videos.
And if you look at the standard approach
today, people take on long videos is
I call this passive perception. Where the
idea is you have, this long, very
long video, decide on some fixed frame
rate, and run a video
caption over the entire frame frame
entire video, and create
a text, database that you can then use to
search or try to the questions.
But this is incredibly inefficient. You're capturing
a lot of frames that potentially are not related
to the question you need to answer And
even if you do that, you may be missing a lot of
details visual
details because you're doing the search over your
over text only.
So what we thought is to think about a
different path we call active
video perception and the idea
is that instead of watching every
everything at once, this AVP treats
the video as an environment, an
interactive environment, where it can iteratively
seek for evidence
that's needed to answer the question.
And because it's a training free framework, we
can deploy it on top of any of the shelf visual
language model. So we can take a look at how
it works. EVP
operates in a continuous loop of
three modules, planning, observation, reflection.
Let me talk a little bit about how each of them
work. First one is about planning
where model here observes
looks at the user query and makes
a decision of where to look within
the video what are the timestamps, the
video, the time interval that I need to
make the observation. And also
how to look. Maybe choose what's the optical
model, frame per second,
FPS, frame rate and the resolution
at which to capture the the images
for that specific task given in
the query. Once you have
that plan, then you can, do
this targeted watch of
the video based on the plan and extract the key
evidence descriptions that may be help
you answer the question.
And finally, you can
do this reflection process where the model itself
assesses if collected
evidence so far is sufficient to answer the question
and if so, it produces an answer. But
if not, it sends all the
current findings back to the planning
module. To re plan and repeat the process
the the rest of the process.
You can run this iterative
loop and process of plan, observe,
reflect until the,
query is is solved.
Okay. So that's AVP in a nutshell.
So let's look at the specific rollout
of an exam of a testing example.
So here we have this query, I
apologize for the small font, but I tell you,
about adding up the millimeter
totals that appear on a sheet of paper
at a specific timestamp in the video of of
ten minutes and then adding up all
the the the lens that appear there
together with some information about
a snake, how long are those snakes,
and and the the question is asking about the total after
adding all those numbers. So to answer
that, you'll need evidence from multiple parts of the video.
You need evidence to look at that piece
of paper, you need evidence to to see where
they were describing the the the snakes.
So so this is what happens
with AVP in the round one, the model plans
a medium spatial resolution
in a very short time span. It already knows
at around minute ten, that's what I need to look
and maybe a a medium special resolution
is enough to read text. So
does that and successfully extracts
the the
from the piece of paper, but then it realizes
that it's missing a piece of information It doesn't
know anything yet about the snake length, so
then it puts together all the information it
has so far send this to to a second
round, a second iteration,
the planner receives this information,
creates a new plan, it realizes that, okay, I
don't know where they are talking about snakes,
so I need to scan over the entire video,
maybe a low frame rate until I figure
out where that is being
discussed. But once it does that,
it does this lowest low frame rate,
low resolution scan, but
it does fine when the range of
the snake lengths are being discussed
and it decides that it has enough information and
accurately responds the
correct option d here. So the
idea again is to use this iterative
process to seek for evidence rather
than passively processing every video.
So AVP, achieves higher
accuracy with significantly less computation using
this strategy. And you can
look at the quantitative results. We
we evaluated this methodology and
multiple datasets and compared to
all existing methods that were
relevant, quite good results. You
can probably look at them more carefully in
the paper. Okay. So that's
what we did on part three with active
perception for long video
understanding, but of course, that's not all. We,
we
they has finished
the main dresser frame and now is
holding a drawer without a handle.
And the screws are on the floor. The user
may ask, hey, what is my next action?
Can you generate a video and show me what
should I do next? And perhaps this video
should be grounded on the specific objects
the user is handling, the specific environment they are
in, and give very precise
motion guidance of what to do.
And in the robot case, maybe the human and the robot
are folding this heavy moving blanket
The robot is holding one corner, the
other one is on the floor, the user,
commands the robot, hey, can you lift this
right side of the bank blanket? So the robot
needs to convert that
command into precise physical trajectory.
So the question is, how can we generate these videos
and action controls for robots
in a way that's guided by fine grained
motions? So that
takes us to our fourth last piece here,
which is about motion guidance generation.
If you look at the prior work,
we see that standard
text to video models struggle to generate
these fine grained motions
unless they are given explicit
manual optical flow guidance.
On the other hand, these VLA models, vision
language action models, can control
robots to perform tasks, but they
require this massive expensive data
set with robot demonstrations that are
difficult to scale. So we're thinking about
these two limitations and in this work, we
try to tackle them by by
first, removing the need to manually provide
motion guidance and second,
be able to to leverage Internet
scale data for training.
So how do we do that? Well, first, let's
talk about how to remove
the need to provide this manual
guidance. So to tackle that first,
issue, we actually proposed to generate the
motion guidance automatically. So we
can learn a model to generate that motion guidance
than having a person to give it manually.
So we call this, method
Future Optical Flow Prediction of Offred
and it converts those input visual
observations and text into explicit motion
representations, in pixel space.
So looking a bit more closely, to
do that, we basically
use a latent diffusion model as a base
architecture. But we train it to predict
future motions. In the case
of this paper, we choose a future
optical flow as an explicit way to
reason about the future motion.
And we can train it using the usual diffusion
loss, But an interesting
key thing and people are if people are using,
diffusion models to predict other
than normal pixels or natural pixels,
we found that it's easier
for the diffusion model to learn how to
predict the optical flow visualization in
RGB. Rather than predicting the
raw vectors of x y
values in in in the image. So interesting
thing that I see now other people reporting
very similar results that
that it's better to just predict stuff in RGB
in a way that maps the actual
raw measurements. So that seems
to be a well replicated point now.
Okay. But the other point I was talking about
is the idea of using Internet
scale data. So for this, we can train
our fourth bread model on
Internet, noisy video caption pairs
that contain human actions.
But a key challenge here is that all these motions
that appear in human videos are very noisy.
There's a lot of background destruction very
difficult to extract
out what is the foreground motion that is actually
important for the task. So we
came up with this,
module to extract this foreground information,
motion information only, and that becomes
the target that our model needs to predict during
training. Okay.
So once we train the system, we,
use it for two types of downstream tasks.
One is video generation and the other
one is robot control. And
just looking a little bit more inside here, we do
that by adding these additional heads
that produce each type of output and which
are fine tuned separately on the
downstream data. Okay. So I'm
gonna wrap up soon. We are gonna look at
some results here where first on video generation,
we see clear improvements compared to
the baseline at the top. In the middle
here is our automatically
inferred motion guidance and the
the row in the bottom is our model
producing a video that really follows the
motions closely as described in the text.
And we see that across number of
qualitative examples. And even some
qualitative results support that too.
Quantitative results support that too.
We also tried this on robot control,
but I guess I don't have much time to talk about this
so I'll skip this. To say
that, yeah, we produce this
motion guidance automatically and are able to leverage
the video data that's on the
Internet to reduce the requirements for
robot control. And that's it. We
have covered this four topics about space
time referencing, the coarse model reasoning,
long videos and AVP, motion guided,
generation and control. And we're
pushing the idea of getting closer
to agentic ambiance intelligence that will
be able to support us doing tasks
but also controlling robots to do more useful
things. And I think for the future, there
are some interesting ideas about how this AI in
human collaborates, more advanced
multimodal reasoning, learning
from experience and so on. So with that, I
wanted to thank you you again for
listening and if we have time for questions, maybe we
can take a couple or otherwise, I'll be around,
to discuss. Yeah. Thank you.
Thanks a lot. Great talk. Yeah.
Let's send our speaker.
And, do we have quest questions
from the audience? If we have questions,
we'll come to the microphone.
Yeah. You can just come here to the microphone
and ask the question.
You mentioned you mentioned that there's some challenge there
with predicting vectors
that you Mhmm. Stuck to the RGB space
instead of vector coordinates.
So do you have a bit more background on that
and why that's happening?
Yeah. It could be it could be
that we don't start this fusion
from turning from scratch. So we reuse
diffusion that's already been, trained for natural
images. So I guess the space
of these visualizations are a bit closer
to the natural image although it's not
that close anyway. But it's a little bit closer
to the space of natural images
than the row r
x y flow values. But
I'm seeing the same thing with other people
trying to predict
surface normals the same thing. If they predict
the RGB, it's better than than than the
raw measurement. So it's seems like people are
seeing this. All around. So maybe
there's insufficient data in the vector
space, right? For now. Could be where then you can
reuse the pretraining RGB that you already have
rather than train from scratch on this specific
thing that there is not much data. Could be. Yep.
Thanks. Perfect.
We have more questions from the audience?
If not, let's thank the speaker again.
And next, we will have our auto session.
Thank you.
Checkmate is secure.
Okay. For the next, we
will have our oral session. We have
three very exciting talks coming.
The first one will be given by
Jacqueline He.
The top title is Anchor Decoding
Probability reducing copyright
risk for any language model. This
is also our award
honorable mention paper
So Thank you.
Okay. Looks like it's here. Jacqueline, take
it over. Yeah.
Okay.
Hi, everybody.
My my name is Jacqueline, and
I'm a third year PhD student at
UW NLP. And today,
I'm here to present our work Anchor
decoding. Provably reducing
copyright risk for any language model.
This work is done with a really
phenomenal set of collaborators at UW
and AI two. John,
Scott Sei Woong, and my PhD advisers
Luke and Pong Wei.
So just to motivate our work a little
bit, as we all know, language
models are pretrained on trillions
of tokens of data. Pretraining
data sets are incredibly diverse
and often contain domains such as books, science,
and math among others. These
datasets are largely constructed by
scraping the open web.
And accordingly, one concern is that
pretraining data may inadvertently include
sensitive or copyright protected material.
So here's one example. The
Lord of the Rings is a such a well known
and widely circulated novel that
it has, intentionally or not, appeared
many times in several common pretraining
data sets. Because it was published
in 1954 and still remains
under copyright in many jurisdictions,
it serves as a useful example of
how protected material can make its way into
training corpora.
So why exactly is this a problem?
Language models can memorize parts of their
training data and later reproduce them verbatim
inference time. This is really concerning
for works protected by copyright, as they
should not be reproduced in an unauthorized
manner. So above is just one example,
Given the opening sentence of the Lord of the
Rings, the model can easily continue with the
exact continuation.
When language models memorize and reproduce
copyright protected data, this can
actually pose several harms to,
several groups. So on one side, data
creators so like authors, artists,
etcetera, whose creative works are
scraped and used for model training,
often did not authorize such usage in the first
place. And are also commonly neither
properly compensated nor credited for the
use of their work. And one current
economic argument is that AI generated creative
work may actually depress demand for some
forms of human creative labor by
crowding out human creative works in the market.
The second problem is for model developers
who may also potentially face legal liabilities
if their models are determined to have infringed
on copyright. Now this is indeed
a bit speculative, given the current
ambiguity of the legal landscape surrounding
this issue, but in recent years,
this has led to several model or dataset
takedowns and now as well as
many ongoing legal court cases.
And I'm not going to get too much
into the legal side of things, but
we can see here that the current legal landscape
surrounding generative AI and
potential copyright infringement is currently very
contentious and unresolved.
So we can see, that as of April
2026, and this is from a fairly
up to date online tracker, there are currently
many active law suits surrounding this
issue, both in The United States
as well as globally across the entire
world. And all this to say, the attempt
to curb the reproduction of copyrighted
works and language models,
is in the best interest of both parties.
So both data creators and model developers.
Of this ongoing debate.
And just before I go into describing
our work, I also want to discuss
some naive solutions to this problem.
So the cleanest way to minimize the
reproduction of copyrighted works
is to remove the high risk data from your pretraining
corpus and retrain your language model.
Such that it never sees sensitive data in the
first place. However, as we all know,
training can be really costly,
and training a model from scratch is already an
expensive endeavor and it's even more
of an uphill battle to retrain all the existing
models that may have already been exposed.
Copyrighted protected material. Another
issue is kind of more practical.
Copyrighted data also tends to be higher quality
relative to other data sources.
So including them wholesale is also suboptimal
for downstream model performance.
So the question that our work seeks to address
today is, how can we elicit
output in a post hoc manner from existing
language models in a way that both
preserves quality while minimizing copyright
risk. Our
work therefore leverages
an emerging ecosystem of what we call safe language
models. Since 2023,
there has been growing development of language models
trained exclusively on curated
permissively licensed data. That is
data not subject to restrictive copyright concerns.
Conversely, risky models encompass
most widely used models today. Their
training data is either undisclosed or likely
to include copyrighted material. In
practice, these models also tend to offer
higher utility and better downstream
performance than safe models. And
this is just to give some concrete examples.
So risky models contain many popular
model families that you likely use in your day to day
research. Including the llama, quin,
and g p t families. And in
our own audits, all of them have been found to
show some tangible degree of copying
of protected works. But on the flip
side, some safe models include the common
line of models, PLAEUS, and KL3M. So these
are a little bit more obscure.
These are, safe models. I have all been
released fairly recently, often as
part of open research initiatives.
And they tend to be considerably smaller than
risky models. They also exhibit
considerably lower copying overlap
but also worse downstream performance compared to
risky models. And to this end,
we propose a decoding method that leverages
both a safe model and a risky model.
We call this anchor decoding. To put
this simply, at each step, we compute
a new output distribution
where the distribution of the risky model is bounded to
that of the safe model within a
user set budget constraint.
So going back to our Lord of the Rings
generation example, there is an empirical
trade off where neither type of language
model actually produces optimal generations.
So consider the input where the prompt
is just the opening line of the novel, which we
first pass to the risky language
model. And we see that the risky
language model produces an output that
from a fluency perspective, it looks pretty
good. But notice that the output is
actually, word for word, the continuation of the next
few lines of the Lord of the Rings. So
from a copying perspective, this is actually
pretty egregious.
But on the other hand, the safe language model
produces a pretty innocuous
output that does not overlap with a ground truth
continuation. If we look at it closely,
it tends to be pretty disfluid. We
can observe some degree of sentence repetition
that a high utility model would not exhibit.
So in all this motivates us to come up with a
new decoding method that
harnesses the benefits of both types of models
while avoiding their respective drawbacks.
Okay. So the next few slides are going to be a
little bit mathematically dense. My
goal is to just give the high level intuition for
our method, there are additional
components and full proofs, but they would be in the paper, and
I'll skip them here for gravity.
So one appealing feature of our decoding method
is that it comes with provable guarantees. To
state those guarantees, we build on a theoretical
framework introduced by Viasat et
al. And inspired by the legal notions
of access and substantial similarity
in copyright law, define a technical
concept called KNAF or k near access freeness.
The idea behind KNAF is simpler than
the math on my slides. So
basically, given a divergence function d,
a non negative information budget
k, and a safe reference distribution p
sub s, output distribution
is k nav compliant if for any
possible sequence it generates,
its divergence from the safe model is always
bounded by k. So k is like your total budget.
Importantly, this is a global sequence level
constraint. That is, it applies to the entire
distribution over continuations up to
some length t.
Rather than to individual tokens in isolation.
And I'll show you that this will be kind of a problem
in just a bit. But
for now, we can really straightforwardly
apply the idea of KNOT to our problem
case, and this lends itself to a
pretty natural constraint sequence level formulation,
where intuitively, we want to find a new distribution,
p star, that approximates
p r or the risky model distribution as
much as possible. Remaining bounded
to the safe model distribution PS
under a global user budget k. But notice
that because this optimization is defined
at the sequence level, solving it directly
is computationally intractable for autoregressive
decoding. As it then becomes a search
problem over an exponentially
large space. This motivates us
to develop a token level local
approximation that can be solved per token
step instead of across the entire sequence.
So notice that the token level
approximation is very similar in form
to the sequence level optimization in the previous
slide. The difference is that we cap
at a local budget k sub t instead of
a large k, in the paper we actually
show different ways to adaptively choose k sub
t. But the bottom line is that if
you choose k sub t in a way such that they
sum up to large k
then this token level local approximation satisfies
the global sequence level ground, and therefore
is KNAV compliant. And in
principle, because the math works itself out really cleanly,
we basically can solve this optimization
at each step and get a pair of weights
for both the safe and risky model. Which
we can then use to obtain a fused distribution
from the two models that we ultimately sample
from. Okay. So
now we're done with the math part, which is good.
But, qualitatively speaking, how good is anchor decoding?
So going back to our Lord of the Rings
example, we can see that the resulting output
is pretty good, at least in in my biased
opinion. It seems pretty original,
I. E. Not derivative of any works
protected under copyright. And the quality is
also much better relative to the safe model's output.
But before we get into empirical results, during
the process, we came across some practical
challenges in our setting. And just to begin,
like many two model fusion methods,
such as contrastive decoding among others,
anchor decoding assumes that the model pairs
are tokenizer compatible. A
sense that they must share a common vocabulary
space. And this is actually really tricky
for our use case as the safe
models that are available tend to have bespoke
tokenizers are not directly
compatible with risky model families. So for
this problem, we have to propose two solutions.
And the first workaround is that for a decoding paper,
we pre train our own language model.
We pretrained our own safe model tiny
comma 1.8 b
that is tokenizer compatible with a LAMA three family.
Full training details are in the paper
but we basically did standard pretraining on
the common pile, which is the largest
permissible license dataset to date.
And just to show some really quick results,
we evaluated tiny, comma, 1.8
b against a range of safe models as well as a
few risky models. It performs
pretty well in a sense that it beats out several
slightly larger safe models, and
catches up to the larger seven b comma models.
However, while tiny comma 1.8
b enables us to do anchor decoding
with a LAMA three models, That's only
one model family. The more ambitious question
is, how can we enable compatibility
with any safe risky model pair?
So the second solution is to convert our decoding
algorithm from token level to the byte
level. And this kind of exploits the observation
that many modern tokenizers are
byte pair encoding based, this allows
us to use ByteSampler, a framework introduced
by my second author John in an earlier
paper that converts any BPA tokenizer
based language model into a byte level model
while preserving its exact generated distribution
at the text level. And I'm not going to
go into too many details here, but essentially
you can think of byte sampler as a black
box function takes in any language
model and returns an invariant byte language
model. And instead of working
in a vocabulary space, we can now do all operations
in a byte space. And since that's basically
the only change, and we show this in
more detail in our paper, The k knot guarantee
still holds theoretically.
So just looking at empirical results,
we report an aggregate of various
literal copying metrics on popular
copyright protected novels from CopyBench.
Which is a copyright measurement
dataset. And we look at
copyright copying risk against two notions
of utility. Long form factuality
using fax score as well as fluency.
We sweep various budgets of k, which
impact practice is a user controllable
knob for the allowable risk budget.
We can see that in our token level
setting, anchor decoding actually works
quite well across both utility cases.
It's just like the purple line, and we can see that
it's Pareto optimal against other
strong copying mitigation baselines for
every choice of k.
Also show that anchored byte decoding
also empirically works effectively. So
here, we are able to try out
a larger range of model pairs that are
not tokenizer compatible.
Using our byte level algorithm. Ingrid byte exhibits consistently
Pareto optimal performance.
So now I want to really quickly motivate why
we think anchor decoding is a useful
method To begin, our method
operates purely at inference time
and does not require any retraining or access
to the original pretraining data.
And unlike many other copying mitigation
methods, which are quite heuristic in
nature, our method also comes with provable
bounds relative to the safe model. And
this is a really useful guarantee when you know the
data provenance of your reference distribution
know that it has not accessed any copyright
material in the first place.
Our method is also user controllable in
the sense that the user can set a preferred
risk tolerance, and finally, our method
retrofits to any off the shelf language
model with exposed latches. So
that means that this allows for the immediate and retroactive
safeguarding of high utility models with
considerable infringement leakage.
Yeah. So that's just like a really quick overview.
If you're interested, feel free to check
out our paper for more details.
And I am interested in kind of follow-up work
in trickier case of copyright
called non literal copying, where it's not like word for
word copying. But semantically,
the text would be still very similar to the
source text. But yeah, here's our
paper with like the QR code to it as well
as the archive ID tag.
Okay. And I think I'm kind of
at time. So I wanna thank everyone for
coming to this talk, and I also wanna thank the workshop
organizers. For all their hard work
in making this event happen. Alright. Thank you
everyone.
Jacqueline, for the great talk. Do I have
questions? We can maybe take one.
I should could you get
prepared? We'll try. I
can ask a question. It's like, I
worked a little bit on, like, this kind of
model merging, like, one
model during decoding time, guided decoding
a little bit myself. We've never made it work.
Because a lot of times, it's quite sensitive
Like, it goes on two extreme case.
Either, like, we completely go to the safe model
or it's not work at all.
So it's always mimic
one model. Did you experience
something similar? Do you have, like,
tuning sensitivity issue for your
Yeah. So we have, like, a budget knob,
like the k. And I think it's
like when k is equal to zero, so you
basically have like no budget for
any divergence, basically clamp to the
safe model behavior, And, conversely,
when k is, like, very large, then that
means that you have basically like infinite budget to work
with. And that basically collapses to the risky
model's behavior. So I think there definitely is some
kind of like tuning thing that you have to do
we actually did have to try, like, some like empirically
some factors k in order to find a
good intermediate. Do you
find it sensitive? To this
k parameter or it's okay? I think
it depends. I would say that,
there's kind of like a range at which after
that particular range, it kind of
plateaus to the risky model's performance.
But I think in general, for token level, it's pretty
consistent. I think for byte level, because
we're working with really different model pairs, it
I think it's a little bit more sensitive.
Okay. Thank you. Let's thank our
speaker again. Yeah. Oh,
yeah. Okay. Yeah. Go ahead. I think
I have a, like, clarifying question. So
so your whole point is there like, if there is a
content which is under copyright,
and if we change the output slightly
then it will not be copyrighted.
But what if, let's say, we paraphrase
the answer.
Will that still be considered copyright?
Sorry. What do you mean by what is answer?
So we'll keep the answer as
it is. Just paraphrase
it. Mhmm. So that it becomes sequentially
equivalent.
Will that be under copyright violation?
Are you talking about, like, the non literal copying
case? I think even in
in your example. Right? If Uh-huh. If one
can just paraphrase it,
Uh-huh. Then is there any
issue with that? If one can just,
like, summarize it instead of going forward,
Yeah. So I think in our case,
we kind of only looked at, like,
basically passages that appear so frequently in
their training data that they're really likely
to be copied word for word And a lot
of our emails are actually focused only on the
literal copying case. But we do also have
some non verbatim, so it's like non literal. It
doesn't have to be word for word, but just like just like
semantically it's so similar enough enough. We
have like a really small set of pilot experiments
in our appendix. And we
did show that I think our work our
method also works pretty well for the nonliteral
setting. I think with, like, nonliteral
copying evaluation, I think evaluation for that is still
very tricky. I see. Yeah. Thanks.
Yeah. Thank you.
Mean, some of these menu. Okay. Some.
Yeah.
Okay. We will have our second oral
presentation in afternoon.
Actually, our episode will give
a presentation on multimodal
data mixtures via light and space
coupling for vision language model training.
What is
Okay. Here it goes. Hello?
Okay. So hi. I'm Arsha,
and I'm here to present the Math Mix,
which is a paper from,
our lab, from one Francesco,
and Volcan, but unfortunately, they couldn't make it,
so I I'm presenting in their
behalf. And I apologize in advance
if, like, I'm not the expert that much in this
domain. Just because, like, I mainly came
here for presenting, my teammate's
work. So today, we're gonna talk about
MATMIX, which is a multimodal data mixture.
Via latent space coupling for VLMs.
And this is the outline of the presentation which,
we give some background and then we mainly dig
deep into the model. And then at the end, we will
gonna give some empirical results, and finally, the
conclusion in future works.
So as you for
sure know better than me, data processing pipeline
for LLMs and VLLMs are existing
on three different stages. One of them is just gathering
the data, cleaning it, second one is like
selecting and and document packing ordering,
and the last one is how to mix this data
to finally actually pass it and parse
it to the LLM. And the VLM
such that it can, train on this one.
We are gonna mainly focus this work is mostly
focused on the third domain, which is how to make
different datas from different modalities.
For VLM training or multimodal training.
And, our method is, developed
for for this stage of training.
And actually, if you wanna take a look at,
how data mixers are in practice,
this is like diagram
from lava one, which is basically showing how
many different domains and modalities of dataset
it is using. Like at
here,
which is using general data,
language, data map, and reasoning OCR, and other
documents. And each of them are different domains
that you can generate the text from.
And, in this this presentation,
we're gonna train these two
different domains as d one d one d one d two on up until
d k, which we have k domains.
We are gonna pretrain on. And And,
for each of these domain, we are gonna have a probability
of how many samples
we're gonna take basically how much each of them
is contributing in our
tuning and post training.
And the question that actually we are gonna ask is
like that how to set up p
such that we can have a good perform performance in,
VLM training. So basically, what's the probability
distribution that are we are going to use for different
domains of the data that we're gonna train on.
On. So one motivation
and, like, that's why
VLM data mixing
is a important problem and a hard problem
first of all, there are, like, many baselines such as,
Dorem, Doge, Rec Rec Rec Rec Rec Rec Rec Rec
Rec Rec Rec And specifically for
multimodal datasets, one of
the challenges like that, it is model. So we
we have different, modalities of text,
images, videos, audios, and so on.
The other one is like that's not all of these datasets
are having all moralities
in it. Like for example, we might,
end up most of the times with pure
text domains or pure image domains.
Like we don't have, for example, caption for the
images that we actually have a multimodal data.
We still wanna know how to handle and these
type of, datasets and how
to what's the probability distribution
that we want to sample from them for our
training? So
now I'm gonna just present, like, briefly
what is matMix pipeline. So
it's it's, it has basically four
different stages. One of them is like that the morality
specific domains that we have like different domains and
for each of them we have different modalities.
Second stage is like that we extract,
we we basically the main point of madamint
is that we map these different modalities
into a shared multimodal space.
Across that shared multimodal space we are gonna
find how much each these each of these modalities
are actually contributing and reflecting our
whole dataset. Something like with the notion
of PCA. And based
on these scores that, like, how much each modality
is contributing to to a
is representing basically our our datasets,
we are gonna use this as
a probability distribution for how we want to mix
this data. And then finally, we train
the VLM with this new mixture
of probability distributions.
So let's dig in. So let
we can start with a single morality case.
Which, we have the input x, which
is lying in a probability distribution that we want
to learn it and this x I i's
are from k different
modalities that we are using.
So for one modality, we basically
we want to learn the shared direction. Which
we are gonna minimize, this loss function
which is basically, rich regression loss.
And then we want to summation of all these
probabilities to be one because of a
probability distribution. And then the score of
how important domain I is is basically
a linear projection into the weight
learned. And basically, this
score is, telling us, for example, if
SI is large, it's showing us that
specific modality is really this specific domain
is reflecting our data and
if this is small, it shows that this is, hard
to reconstruct our database. On only
the single modality. And,
so as I measures how well,
domain I represent the shared geometry of our
dataset. So
So if you just, apply the primal
dual, for
for this simple optimization problem and, like,
take the Lagrangian and then compute the gradients
And Basically, we find out, like, that, the
alpha Ga for the Lagrangian is gonna
be having this form, which is basically like as all of you
know from simple linear regressions.
And, here k is the kernel
matrix between different to, basically
different to modalities of x.
And the score is, as as mentioned in the previous
slide is gonna be just computed using
like a projection. Basically if you project,
we'll end up in this one.
Now,
let's jump into the multimodality
part a bit. So
we first extract each
embedding for each modality independently.
And here we're gonna denote x I v as the embedding
of the modality v into the domain I.
And now we're gonna move basically to the
key part of matmix which is projecting
these into, shared space alpha,
which is which we call cross model
coupling. And,
basically optimizing this such that, like, we find
that what is the probability distribution of each modality
that we're going to use in in
the training. So
and now, actually, another another important
thing is, like, that as we mentioned, like, we
might end up many times for datasets
that, like, for domains that, like, we are missing
some morality. In order to avoid,
using those domains with a
morality in our
final
final calculation. We actually indicated
that the
indicator function here that like
it's basically zero one one if if the
modality is present in that specific
domain So basically, if if it is present, it's
one, and then we actually include the data for that modality.
But if the modality is not present and it's
absent, we set the indicator to zero and therefore
also the x I v to zero. So I should we make sure that
we are not use, we
are not injecting noise in our
in our fine foundation of the probability
distributions. And then simply
like this is basically
the solve solving the linear regression
problem. And, we
end up with the alpha, s
then basically, very close to the single
modality domain, which are different that we have an indicator
function here to remove the mixed mod
to remove the modalities that they are not
present in our domain and also
KMM is again like the
linear linear kernel that we are using.
And after finding d s, basically, we find
a probability distribution which is
simply a soft max over the over d s functions
that we have seen so far. We
are actually gonna use this probability distribution from now
on as a data mixture,
as our mixing
probabilities. Instead of uniform or average
or, like, human based, choosing.
Well, now that we have been through
them, let's actually go a little bit dig into our
experimental setup. Like, we
are the experiments of this paper are,
focusing on visual instruction
tuning in Lava one which is
the stage two. If you're
considering the pipeline of tuning
for Lava one. And, we
are gonna compare with different baselines, which one of them
is uniform, basic giving equal ways to
all different, modalities that we are using.
Second one is a human, which basically
humans it's it's aligned with human
like humans have literally scored how much of each
data we need to use in in training.
And, average, which is the average of unit
model ways then fuse which is, weight
from early fused embeddings.
Well, actually, if we look at matmix,
matmix is, as we can see, like,
the final, results of mad mix are
not uniform and they are,
they are actually giving more weights ones that
are more reflecting our data and less weight
to the ones that are not reflecting that
much the whole whole dataset.
Then we can see that actually, mat mix
beats uniform with 56%
of the steps. And,
matches human in 78% of
the training steps. So
Also, here is, some more detailed
benchmarking which, Mad Mix
shows clear advantage
compared to average and fused.
And, we can actually
transfer rates from LAMA zero
point b to seven b.
And, yeah, it's also the same.
Also, like, for final notes, like,
our as as you might have seen, like, that we are generating
this kernel linear kernel function, you might
you might think that, like, this this might be cubic
or quadratic. So come
computationally complex. But, basically, we
want to say that it's not that complex because,
this this is cubic over the
number of domains.
And, usually k is very small. Like,
we don't I mean, compared to for example sequence
lengthings transformer, it's not like 1,000, it's
something around like
ten twenty or so, and then this would not introduce
a significant overhead during the training.
So at the end of the day, we we end up with,
we should like it's it's compute
kinda efficient compared to other approaches.
I mean, it's it's more computationally
heavy, but not that heavy and it's still efficient
to to calculate. So
last thing is like that we have also added,
video QA domain,
video text per data in
two video benchmarks and also we have seen for
both Lava half 7,000,000,000,
mad mix is still outperforming the uniform
distribution. And,
lastly, here is, like, the
summary. And future durations.
So MATMIX turns VLMs into a
lightweight latent space. So we project
them and then we extract the
probability distribution from there. And then it handles
some missing modalities, which can be a case for
many different trainings. Improves accuracy
efficiency, and at the end of the day, it's not like
that computationally
demandy. It's pretty efficient.
Some future directions are online
methods, how to adjust domain weights
during BLM training and how to
do domain definitions and
then modality interactions.
Better cross model
may further improve data mixings.
And, lastly, I want to just
share the QR code and thanks
I mean, basically, like, the author of the
original authors of the paper, one unit
Francesco. And I will invite you that in case you
have any questions or any unclearities or
actually there's anything that you're interest
on, please feel free to reach out to them
as they would
be pretty happy to answer, and they know it's way
more than Thank you so much for
listening, and
yep, This is it.
Thanks, Ashir, for giving the presentation.
Behalf of the authors. So
we have questions or do we want to leave
the question to the authors? I think those authors
are happy to Yes. I mean,
you have questions on other domains, I would be
happy answer on sequence modeling, but I'm I'm
not, like, very expert in
data machine. Yeah. Let's thank,
Akshay again, and, we
will have our last oral
presentation. You. Thanks.
Okay. As we are come our source
speaker,
maximating
Yeah.
Okay. We will have our third
and,
final oral presentation
the afternoon and for today's workshop.
Now the final presentation we still have a
invited speaker later. But this
is our last contributed talk.
So this presentation
will be given by Maximilian
Idel and the
the the title is
popular one, multi property
document annotation large language model
data curation at scale. Take
it away. Thanks. Yeah.
Hi, everybody. I'm Max. Nice to meet you guys.
Hope you have had a great conference so far.
Yeah. Presenting today is some work from us
at Eleamind. We are a small, but
mighty startup in Germany working on evaluation.
But yeah, today's I'm presenting of course some some
data stuff.
Yeah, propeller one. Essentially, so
to us it felt like since
a cup it's quite a while now since since
fine web edu, Most in
most work on free training data curation has
kind of relied on this yes, kind of
single score paradigm
we like to call it which essentially means, okay,
try to reduce a large pool
of of text data down to a high quality
subset. By, yeah, thresholding on some
on some scalar scores. Usually,
I don't know, produced with small models
like fast text or or small encoder
models. Of course, mostly because
you need to, like, process billions of documents
and score them.
And this kind of comes with a couple of issues. So
for example, it can, like, conflate different
quality dimensions and also
bias towards certain topics. And
also it's like kind of yeah.
It focuses really on a narrow definition
of high quality sometimes.
So kind of six months ago,
we kind of came to this problem where we wanted
to generate some German synthetic datasets
and had, like, some struggles into picking
a good seed dataset to start from.
So we were kind of like, okay, let's
just build our own solution to
enable us being able to pick good seed
data sets or synthetic data We
also kind of wanted to have some good insights into
into pretraining datasets like
looking at some compositional structure of them,
and of course the overarching
goal that always is there of yeah,
we want to have trained better models through better data
curation. So
And we hope that Propeller actually enables
all three
So, yeah, what is Propeller? First of all, I
kind of see it as even like a
framework. So we
kind of had the goal of annotating a document
with properties. That's also
why the name Propeller kind of came to be.
So it's a property
annotation model. From LAMIND.
And essentially, it contains like a framework
of 18 properties that are being annotated
for each document. And they
are like these let's say six overarching
categories or some core
content annotations, some classification annotations.
Some quality and and value of the data
judges, some
annotations defining audience and
purpose of documents, something
on safety and also something on geographic
relevance because we were also kind of
interested in building models that
are like better cultural
culturally aligned.
You see these properties also can have like
different types. So most of them are ordinal.
In the bottom, I put an example for the
commercial bias properties. So you go from
none no commercial bias to
some minimal bias to moderate to heavy.
Or to, let's say, pure marketing documents.
And same applies for for the other ordinal
ones. We also have
a couple of multi select properties,
so for example business sector,
where essentially the model picks
the list of business sectors this document might
belong to out of out of 37 different
business sectors, We
also have one single free
text property, which is like a one sentence subscription.
That's being generated for each document.
So how did we
did we get to these 18 properties? It's like a question
I get all the time.
It was not an easy process,
but essentially in the beginning, we just asked
GPT five, hey, I
now want to build this nice and fancy property
annotation model for free
training. Data curation and
kind of ask it, hey, what are the properties
I might want to consider and make
a very extensive list So I don't
know, it came up with like a 200, 300
different property list. And of course
that kind of is a bit out of proportion.
But essentially, we took like two weeks of of iterating
on this on this property list
pruning some, merging some,
sharpening also some some guidelines
and rubrics and also lots of
disambiguating. Finding edge
cases, putting some, let's say, examples
or difficult ones to help the model
and in the end kind of arrived at one
property annotation guideline
that kind of really defines these 18
properties.
Yeah. All with all with like fixed schema
or type values
It's rather long so it's if you want to read
all of it, it's gonna be a
while. You can find this
definition at this link.
But I'll also put up a QR code later on.
So here's an example on how this how
this very long rubric looks like.
For one of the properties. So this is like a literal
excerpt. From there for for commercial
buyers. So essentially, it always starts with like
a rough definition of what
we are measuring in like a one sentence summary
and then of course defines all the different
values the property can take and
defines also for each of these values
when it should be picked. So
that also a human could technically
reproduce kind of this judgment of of
annotation.
In the bottom, you also see that for each of these values,
we always put some some examples
to to make it easy for the model to pick one of
these.
So
Yeah. And then we kind of kind of had this question of,
okay, in the optimal case, we would
just now use this this
annotation guideline and just ask the best LLM
to annotate all of our documents.
But of course, if we if we do
that then we'll go broke in API credits
rather quickly. So we kind
of said, okay, now we need to build the
smallest but best model that
can actually do this task. Well
So we tried a couple of, let's say, distillation
approaches trying to have frontier,
yeah, huge reasoning models, commercials,
annotate a diverse document
sample So on the right, I put some tables so you can
see like where did we pick data
from to annotate initially. So
we aim for like a very broad coverage of your
typical pretraining data
sets and also languages.
You can also see we included some code
math and SFT data because we want the model
to also be able to annotate
that.
And another big aspect was that we also
had to collect lots of bad documents
because yeah. Well, if you want to build a model that
is able to help you filter
data, it also needs to see bad
documents during training. Right?
And actually, one one fun aspect was
that there were of course some documents
that no frontier model kind
of wanted to annotate well, so we had to
actually also annotate a couple of them by
by hand.
Yeah. Then then we we trained a couple
of models on these on this data.
23 based models So both
three variants essentially for the
1.7 b, and point six b. Also wanted to kind
of see how many parameters do we actually
need to to do such an annotation task
well.
And they have long context support. We have
57 languages in total. And
all of these models essentially output JSON.
So you feed them a text document. So here
I put an example, hi, it's me, Max.
And the model always responds in the same
fixed JSON schema. So here you
can see an example output. Right? So it's
says here oh, yeah. One sentence description for
this document is, short personal greeting
introducing someone named Max. Great.
And it also says,
great content essentially. Yes. Very
safe.
So we evaluated these models of course
as well to kind of see how
well does did our training work out.
So what we essentially did is pick a 3,000
document heldout set and annotated it with
the back in December
let's say best model available
as by our definition, which back then just
came out Gemini three Pro and of
with highest reasoning effort. Yes. We
kind of see an upper ceiling and like annotator
quality. And
then compared a bunch of, yeah, baselines
against our models So of
course, we were quite interested in seeing how
let's say, our models compared to Gemini three
flash because essentially one would
assume that Gemini three flash has a let's
say, closely aligned performance to a Gemini
three pro. Right? And what we
essentially measured is is the agreement with
the reference annotator, which is yeah,
Gemini three Pro on the
y axis. And essentially for each of these
properties measured how well does do,
yeah, propeller models agree
with this reference annotator.
And, yeah, turns out they they do quite well.
The the four b model lens, let's
say, just above Gemini three flash
and I don't know when we first saw these these
numbers, we were like, oh hell yeah.
We would have loved to annotate all documents
with Gemini three three flash at scale.
So yeah, we're pretty happy But also,
we're very happy about the performance of the very
small point six d model, which does
a very reasonable job for
its for its size.
So
We then were of course very interested into in
starting producing these annotations at scale.
For yep, people to use mostly
and to to run lots of downstream experiments.
So we kind of spend a
bunch of time on optimizing, yeah,
serving of these models.
And finally landed with some,
yeah, s g lang config plus
plus LL guidance. So the yeah.
Framework to enforce, structured outputs.
And make it fast.
VLM somehow did not work out super
well for us,
So at each at each inference, we
essentially strictly enforced
this annotation schema. So
yeah, you can be sure that all model outputs
are valid And
we also do not produce any white space during
inference to save tokens.
You can see here some some throughput numbers
we we estimated for a couple of
datasets.
And we also did some quite big
runs already on lots of GPUs.
On the right side, you can find a
repository here that's called Propeller annotations.
Essentially provides you lots and lots of
annotations for yeah, popular
free training data sets. So by now, we produced
over 14 b which is,
quite a lot. And
And I have to say that we mostly focused for now
on producing non English
annotations mostly because,
the EU is happy to fund us with compute
for doing non So
But sure happy to collaborate if you have
computer spare to annotate English data as
well at scale.
So, yeah, if you have suggestions on on
datasets to annotate, please reach
out.
And you can use these annotations to
yeah, come up with some cool
dataset inside experiments, on the
fly. So for example,
in this in this heat map, we have
essentially annotated NemoTron CCD
data, which then was kind of
the one of the better
publicly known free training datasets that
produced good models.
And we specifically were interested in like, okay,
how good is actually their quality scoring?
And what we essentially did is annotated a couple
of documents for each of their
quality tier definition on the x axis
and on the y axis, you essentially see a couple
of propeller properties and how they
yeah, correlate with the new normal CC annotations.
And and yeah, for example,
the insight is that even the Neutron
CC high quality tier has
of course lots of bad documents still
don't know, lots of heavy marketing bias.
Many have very thin information density or
or incomplete.
And this is something yeah. The quality
score did not really capture.
So
It's also really really nice to
yeah, use
propeller annotations. It's really really easy to
to get to or to compose
filters for good data sets rather quickly.
So here's an example where I just pointed Claude
at the documentation of Propeller.
Kind of told it
from a user perspective, yeah, hey, I need a high quality
reasoning heavy dataset to
train a finance model I don't know, maybe
I want to have an LLM in the finance domain and
have wanted to do really well and also
told it that it should not
yeah, include commercially biased text.
And don't need to have the
ads of my competitors in my dataset,
And essentially, what it can then do is like
define this duct
DB style or SQL style query over the
annotations and simply compose
a couple of filters So here you see,
okay, it says quality content quality
needs to be good and excellent. And reasoning
indicators, property needs to be analytical
or explanatory, and the business
sector needs to be from financial service.
And so on. And then it's kind of rather easy
to, yeah, compose
datasets flexibly.
So, You can also do this
much more fancy, so if you just tell it, hey, please
give me the top 100,000 documents for
pretraining a model, it will
start coming up with fun and fancy
filters. So here's one where it defines
like a quality score from zero to
24, by combining
bunch of propeller properties.
So
Yeah. Where where I see where do
I see this heading? So
what I'm also really interested in working
on now is, let's say, automating
a bunch of data curation stuff.
Of course, moving into the age of maybe automated
research with with agents.
So what we are looking into now is doing some
automated data mixing So maybe
you've seen the the Climb mix paper from NVIDIA
as well. So essentially
here, we start from
having some propeller annotated datasets
So can be flow And
let's say, a fixed small scale train and
evaluation. Setup for training
model and evaluating on some downstream
tasks. And then
you can, like, define some quick loop of
having an agent that iterative iteratively
yeah, proposes some candidate filters based
on propeller notations applies
them submits a job to the
cluster,
run some evaluation, and then based
on this evaluation result kind of
starts refining, its candidate filters
and you can kind of loop
this until you are satisfied with with
EVAL performance or until it's saturates.
So
Yeah. I think that's it for for today.
Thanks for listening. I put a QR code here.
You can find all models and data and everything
And everything under
Apache or CC BY licenses, so everything
permissive. Yeah. Finally, I have to
post it later. Yeah.
Thanks.
Thanks, Max, for the talk. If
you have question, please come to the
microphone.
Yeah. Hey. Thanks for the talk. Just
short comment on the datasets.
That should be labeled. I think the
CRM of course, will make sense.
It's a standard in community, and
having text there would
help a lot, I think, to, do experimentation
altogether given that there are so many baselines with
DCLM. Right? Yeah,
thanks.
Okay. Thank you very much
for the talk and for the for the work. I think it's
super, super valuable and super, super interesting.
I was just wondering, like, two questions, whoever
has questions. One is, have
you done included or considered
any potential for
like
adversarial in a way
people injecting things into a document
to gain this model
in case it became popular. I can
I can imagine already a new
sale technique of including a give
this document a
super high score in absolutely every and
everything?
So far we have not, but I would
actually argue that our approach is probably less
prone to up adversary examples mostly because
of course the let's say, four b model
is probably better in understanding
documents and if you compare to for example
a quality score that is maybe fast text based
and just uses n grams, it's probably
easier for an adversary to just inject a bunch
of engrams to
influence a quality score.
But sure. I mean, we have no
protections against that for now.
Maybe maybe so we put propeller minus one,
maybe minus two can
look into this. But so far, I Okay. That's
I'm not thought about this. No. For the future.
And the second one is, you have said that
you have been working on non English
documents and non English work.
Like, I'm from the Basque Country, for example, and we
have like this super
great language that is
very hard to manage with many with many
I think we support best Yes. You support
it. Okay. I was going to ask you how
how down you go and how well
does Propeller work with with non native. So so you
see on the slide of URL m, which
a project we're involved in and essentially they have a list
of languages they want to
support and I think all EU languages
are there. So That's
awesome then. Congratulations for the for
the work. Thanks.
Thanks for the great talk, Ed. Two quick questions.
So one, I guess you generated the evaluation
data using Gemini three, and I guess
a lot of the criteria are very subjective, like medium
versus medium high.
Would you know how much Gemini
three itself score on this
criteria? Like, if you resampled
these labels again, how much would the agreement
be from the No.
It's for sure a good question.
Also, I mean, might even be very
different let's say, judging between maybe
Gemini or GPT or
Claude right by switching the reference annotator.
And yes, I think there's also, let's say, lots of
science behind to do it
We were more like, okay. Let's ship an artifact
as fast as possible. And
just assume any of the, let's
say, frontier commercial models will do
a very good job on annotating these
data things.
But sure. Another open
point is, of course, maybe on how
open models could do it. Right? So I don't know, Akini
cave two five or DeepSeq and how
they would actually compare
As mentioned for us, it was mostly important
to let's ship the artifact as fast
as possible and try to ship the best artifact as fast
as possible. So we just went with the
best guess, let's say. Yeah. I
guess maybe a related question,
you I guess for some of the downstream task,
like, if I want to select 100,000 documents
from this, out of, whatever,
14,000,000,000,
guess the cost of false positives versus false negatives
is very asymmetric. So
you have sort of
evaluations on which
way the errors go, when there are errors? So far,
not much.
So far, we're mostly interested in evaluating, let's
say, actual training impact
of of these filters, like
do these filters actually make better models? Right? This
is like the the ultimate goal, of course.
And to to do this, we kind of need to actually train
something with it.
But, no, so far, we've not done much,
false positive analysis yet. No.
Thanks. But for sure interesting thing to
do. I think in general, lots of lots of
open questions that this kind of
surfaces now. Yeah.
Let's uncover our speaker again.
Next, we will have the coffee break and
please come back for our keynote talk.
And the the rest of the session. See
you soon.
Hi, folks. We will have
plenty of time to look at the posters later.
Could you take a seat? Let's start
our last
session.
If you have friends outside,
taking a break, let them know. We will
start our next session.
So we will have our last
keynote speaker, and then we have a sponsor
talk. Hope everybody can
come and, enjoy the talk.
Please take a seat if you are in the room.
Okay. So let's get started.
This is our last session
in the afternoon. Thank you,
everybody, for staying with us.
Our next keynote
speaker Fred Sala.
And, Fred is an assistant professor
in the computer sciences department at
the University of Wisconsin Madison and
the chief scientist at Snorkel AI.
His research studies the fundamentals
of data driven systems and the
machine learning. With a focus on data
centric AI and the foundation models.
Previously, he was a postdoctoral
researcher at Stanford and received
his PhD in electric engineering
from UCLA. He and his
group received the 2024 DaPa
Young Faculty Award UW
Medicine, SESUM,
the student's choice professor
of the year award, best
student paper runner at UAI.
That's welcome, Fred.
Nothing? How about now?
Okay. I'm normally loud enough to hear
about a microphone even back there, but let's, let's
make it work. So starting over. So thanks
so much to everyone for coming to the talk and also to
the organizers. For putting on a
great event. So I'd like to talk a little bit about kind
of what we think of as the art and science
of benchmarking agents. This
is something we're very excited about at Snorkel.
I'll talk a little bit about kind of how we think
about these things. Send out
a few hot takes hopefully, We'll
also talk a little bit about a grant program
that we've kicked off at Snorkel We'd love
see if folks are interested, especially,
it's about collaborating with us to build the next
generation of benchmarks. And then finally,
I'll walk through one example of a new benchmark we're
working on that I'm very excited about.
So let's get started. The motivation for
this talk is really about the fact that
interestingly, it's become much much easier
to develop new AI systems, models,
agents, compared to evaluating
them and measuring them. And our
guess is that this gap is really gonna be
something that continues to grow over
time. And as a result, we have all of these
things we don't really know how well they
work we have an increasingly hard time actually
bowing and measuring them. Them. So if
we want to go close this gap
we expect that there's gonna really be a
full toolkit that you actually have to go
use. So at Snorkel, we're very excited,
of course, to go in the field with a lot of
the folks that we work with and really understand
exactly what they're doing in real production
environments and their own domains. Also
big believers, for example, in red teaming and
all kinds of other evaluation tools.
But the piece that we're still very excited
about is really open benchmarks.
And although, of course, we're aware of the risk of
bench maxing and kind of related behaviors,
we still think that open benchmarks are really
going to actually shape the field
going forward. And so we think that we need
more diverse open benchmarks And
this is really gonna be the path for us to
build agents that we can actually reliably use.
So kind of thinking through this, we decided recently
to start an open benchmark grant
program. So this is something that we've done in collaboration
with a bunch of other great organizations. So
Hugging Face, PrimeIntellect together, and a bunch of
other folks. And it's a commitment
basically to help researchers
in academia and in industry get the resources
they need to try out
their kind of newest and greatest and most field
changing types of benchmarks. So I'll talk
a little bit about this program, especially at the end.
We'd love to hear your ideas if you're interested
participating as well. So
as a result of looking at what came
out to be something like a 150 applications
that we've gotten so far for this program,
we've really had a lot of time to think through
what kind of makes a benchmark
particularly good. Right? What are the real
aspects of a benchmark that concretely
make it successful And
then similarly, what are the kind of more
interesting, more latent concepts that make
for these really great field
changing driving forward kinds of
benchmarks. And we've come down to this taxonomy
that kind of splits up these properties into
the more scientific aspects. Right? What are the concrete
things that you have to have have a great
benchmark? And then what we think of as more
like the art. Right? Like what kind
of intuition and what kind of real bets do you have
to make to create a benchmark that's
really going to move the field forward?
So I'll try to go through all of these and give a few
examples as well. From a lot of
the benchmarks that have been super successful in
the past and that have also really
inspired us at Snorkel and that we kinda keep in
mind when we go build a lot of new benchmarks
ourselves. So in terms of
what makes benchmarks really effective,
as measuring sticks in particular, the
one that we really often focus on is
what the quality of the data and the tasks
are really like. And of course, quality is something
that you have to go measure in numerous ways.
It's also something that's really evolved pretty significantly
in the past. So the one kind of
benchmark I love and that I'll highlight is GPU
QA. And it's sort of
one of these benchmarks that tracks the evolution
of what you see from the past. Which
were often kind of much more
simpler types of benchmarks. To something
that's now very sophisticated to build in order
to maintain the highest possible quality.
So I think if you go back in time and look at early
QA efforts, a lot of those benchmarks really
came down to let's scrape some questions off
the Internet and get as much coverage as we possibly
can. Maybe there wasn't such a focus at
the time on making sure those questions weren't
correct. Unambiguous, etcetera.
And as a result of that, these things are very useful
and shape the field but they often had
some problems. And what I like about
things like GPQA is that the offers have really
fought this fruit quite a lot. And they created
this really complex system
of incentives to try to make sure that the problems they
built were actually perfectly correct,
unambiguous, and so forth. So
the way they actually do this is basically they hire
creators or offers for these problems
along with expert reviewers Now
unfortunately, the typical incentive
is if you pay these folks by the hour, they'll try
to produce as much stuff as possible and that
will be it. Right? The offers will create lots of
questions. The reviewers will review
and pass lots of these questions as a result.
So what these folks have done is really build the system
of incentives. So for example, they'll
do things like if the offer writes
a question, they get paid a certain amount.
But if that question is passed by
reviewers, they get a bonus, for example.
If the reviewers all agree independently,
that there is something valuable in a question, they also
get a bonus. If they all agree there's something bad
or flawed about a question, they end up getting a bonus
as well. So it's this really intricate system
of economic incentives It really
is derived from things like mechanism design,
but it's become incredibly powerful in
data creation. You can't really get by
without having this kind of system. So this is something
that I've really appreciated, and it's inspired a lot of
the ways that we create our benchmarks too.
Kind of moving on toward diversity. So I think,
of course, this is one of the most important aspects
of building a good benchmark. So we'll highlight
the classic here like MMLU, where
they had a huge number of categories.
Different questions in each category based on kind of what
typical users see. We often
do things like define a taxonomy and
sort of very
Difficulty, of course, is the most interesting and most
challenging aspect of building benchmarks today.
So we want to create questions that are hard enough
for models that there's enough room for models
to climb so they're not saturated. On
the other hand, these questions have to be valid.
Right? So you can't cheat by creating
impossible questions in order to meet this difficulty
bar. So RKGI has been really great
at this. That's one of the benchmarks that we're
often inspired by. They often start with
versions that have something like one or 2%
accuracy. So are really challenging for models,
and then only gradually do you see solutions that
start really climbing there. So they
are really amazing at building unsaturated
benchmarks. And finally, of course,
making sure that you have a robust methodology
for evaluation is equally important
is something that we spend a lot of time on, and I'll
give a shout out to Tao Bench for inspiring a lot
of what we end up doing at Snorkel as well.
So all of these facets are really important to take
into account They'll all produce benchmarks
that are really usable and that tell you good information.
You have to kind of go beyond this if you're interested
in building a benchmark that really potentially
changes or shapes the field. So this
is more getting into the art It's
really about sort of guessing what will come next.
The frontier is gonna look like in the future,
and building something around that. So
this is something much more difficult in a way
Our thinking is that there's a couple of things
in common for all the real game changing
benchmarks. If you have these,
there's a good shot you have at doing it.
So for example, most of these
benchmarks, they have a real thesis
about where the field is gonna go.
And they make a bet on it. And so
for one example, we love terminal bench.
And here's a quote from Mike Merrill, who's won the
creators of TerminalBench. Right? He basically
says, our big bet is that in
the future, something like 99%
or 95% of LLM computer interaction
is through the terminal. And that's something that we've
really gotten accustomed to lately, but it wasn't
really an obvious thing given the huge
space of options you could have.
But making this bet and really intuiting
what was going to happen the future has made things like
terminal bench incredibly impactful.
Similarly, if you have a good road map for
the field, think that keeps a lot of these benchmarks
quite fresh and useful. So of
course, sweep bench has been incredibly important as
well. But one thing we love about it is that it
wasn't sort of a static single benchmark.
That was there. It actually was something
that grew and evolved with a bunch of different
versions that were tackling different needs.
So the original sweet bench, sweet bench light
verified these newer multilingual
and multimodal versions. All of these things
have sort of gotten added value over
time. Have kept it useful for many,
many years. Similarly, we
think there's an aspect of how well
researchers can interact with this kind
of work that makes for a really impactful
benchmark. Just a couple
of things that I'll highlight here. So for example, Helm and its common
interface was super useful.
And similarly, Harbor, which is a framework for
agents that was built alongside terminal
bench, has really kind of made things easy
a lot of people to go do experiments.
So having make sure that this kind of frictionless
environment exists for researchers to use your
benchmarks we think that's something that really
produces a lot of value.
So this is kind of our our general hot takes on
what makes for a good benchmark. And really what
drives these things forward. We've also
recently been thinking quite a lot about things like
four agentic benchmarks in particular.
What should these things have? What
will really make them useful?
How do we create the taxonomy that
kind of specifies what matters and perhaps
what doesn't for building a good agentic
benchmark. And we've come up with this kind
of free access definition There's
lots of ways to kind of slice it. But
we
think this is one of the simplest ways that can characterize
a good agentic benchmark. We
start from something like environment complexity.
Right? So how rich and how dynamic
is the environment that our agents are gonna operate in?
How autonomous are gonna be these agents,
so our autonomy horizon, how independent do
we want them to be? And finally, we look at
their outputs, how rich, how complex are the outputs
from these agents. So just kind
of walking through these, and I'll give an example
a new benchmark we're building that I'm very excited
by. So environment complexity is, of
course, incredibly important. Because
ultimately, there's a big gap between the complexity
of the real world actual deployments
of agents, and what we build in
any kind of benchmark, any kind of system.
So here, for example, imagine that we're using
an agent to do something like you know,
introduce new users to a system.
Onboard them, Right? There's all kinds
of crazy situations that will happen there
something that can take a long time have
many many subtasks, might be all kinds
of changes to the company, the schema, etcetera,
that take place during this process.
These are all complexities that are not sort of obvious
for us to build but are incredibly important if you
wanna have something truly realistic.
So some angles that we really care about for these,
right, how domain specific is
the benchmark gonna be? And
ultimately, how much real knowledge is not
stored any particular place,
but rather in the minds of people, are
things that we often end up caring about.
Similarly, how complex is
the context? Multimodal is this
gonna be? Our favorite which is tool
complexity, A lot of our different agentic
systems ultimately struggle the most with tool
usage. It's still a big challenge for
agents who will often hallucinate tools or
fail to use them reliably. And then finally,
how we interact with other agents and also human
users both in terms of
coordination complexity, and how complex
that communication will be. So
turning to autonomy, this is basically just a
question of how long do we expect this
agent to be able to sort of adequately
continue before it really breaks down.
Is it going to be something that's going to
take tens or hundreds or thousands of steps?
How complex is that world going to be?
How much do our agents need access to
a world model? To efficiently explore?
And finally, these goals that they're going to be tackling
how non stationary? How diverse are they gonna
be? How much will they change over time as well?
So this is something that really characterizes a
lot of kind of what we expect our agents to
be able to do. And then finally,
the output complexity is sort of the most
obvious one here, Right? How sophisticated
is the output, the deliverable, gonna be?
Our agents are gonna produce? Increasingly,
our agents are not expected to just sort of do
one particular thing. They have much
more multifaceted outputs that they have to
be able to produce. We have to build
very nuanced rubrics and rewards
systems for them. Otherwise, we'll immediately struggle
to do anything. Of course, our outputs also
have to be very trustworthy. So this is
kind of all I wanted to really chat about in
terms of sort of how we see the space
of benchmarks, especially for agents,
also want to use one particular example that we're
working on both in my academic group,
but also with snorkel's open benchmark
program. And it's called Slopcode
bench. We picked this name kind
of to be as provocative as possible after
exploring a big space of them. But
the basic motivation is really the fact
that AI is producing vast
amounts of slot really across
every kind of data modality that you can think
of. And this is a
problem everywhere. But maybe, you know, having
to see too many annoying fake AI
videos on Twitter is not as
damaging as what we get as a result of
code slop. So we've seen actually tons
of issues that have come up now that anybody
can run their code agent and produce whatever
output they like. There are, for example, organizations
that no longer work with external contributors.
They no longer take PRs.
Because of the fact they're being inundated with tons
and tons of code slop. And it
takes a long time to review and to make sure anything
there is reasonable. This is kind of
one of the challenges that have come with
these amazing dramatic advancements
in code agents, especially in the last six months.
So the the first question that we really started thinking
about when building this benchmark is
how do we actually go measure SLOP?
In fact, what does swap really even
mean in any sense here?
And one thing that we really kind of came up with
as a central property is
something like SLOP should be something measured
over iterative process
So you have two examples that you see here.
Of just some simple functions that a code agent
wrote. The first one's in response to
being asked to do some kind of search.
It's an okay function. As
a single sort of time point, as a single request.
It's maybe okay for our purposes. Maybe this
is not really where swap is such a big deal.
The real problem starts happening when we ask
the model to do something different starting
from that point. When we sort of add a
second, a third, a fourth point, when we have
this more long running iterative process,
then we really see slops starting to take
hold. So for example, if you make some
modification to what you did initially,
the agent doesn't really know how to make the simplest
and most effective possible modification
to the code. It'll start adding a bunch
of stuff. It doesn't think through very carefully
about how to refactor code. It just says, let me
add some more cases and I'll handle whatever
I'm being asked to handle. So kind
of taking this example and trying
to build more of a knock actual framework
around it, we came up with something that looks a little bit like
this. We have some initial
spec that you see on the left over there Let's suppose
that it's an example like doing some basic
code search. And our agent does a reasonable
job It produces a solution with
two files over there, and maybe the quality of the solution
is reasonable. Then we ask
the agent to do some modification which is
sort of tracking a very realistic standard
process that we typically have in software development.
Adding some new features. Right? So for example, maybe
we handle some new programming languages
this case, the agent says, okay, let me
add some more to take care of these new
So
This is probably not necessary. We could probably
refactor and do it with a much smaller delta
but instead we're just adding more lines.
And we keep doing this with more and more updates,
each time creating the sort of massive
construct that becomes incredibly difficult
to maintain, to review, to extend,
and so forth. This is the basic
idea. We went forth and kind of built
an actual benchmark around this idea.
All of our problems are basically check pointed,
so they have multiple iterations.
The basic idea is just that we give a natural
language specification to our agent. We
have a set of tests that we can use to measure
performance. And then each agent is
just basically given the natural
language for the next iteration
along with the workspace that it's performed so far.
So you just basically have everything the agent's done
so far plus the new thing it's being asked to
do and we keep track of what's going on
there. Alright. So we're at
DataFM. And so far, I haven't really talked about data
too much. So where is our data
coming from? Turns out that building these
kinds of checkpointed problems is not super
trivial. Haven't built a huge number
because each one has multiple components. So we're
at 40 and growing so far. In
fact, if anybody has contributions they'd like to make,
would be wonderful. Just a shameless plug there.
Most of these problems while they have some synthetic
components, a lot of them are really manually
built. They have to be sort of carefully designed
to make sure they make sense. Then we verify
them all manually as well. So we have
a bunch of examples over here, including some truly strange
ones. We've done a bunch of tasks that are like inspired
from video games that have incredibly high complexity.
And actually these agents are quite bad on.
How do we actually measure swap
the other sort of question that's interesting here is
there's some interplay, right, between slop
and performance. You could have sloppy
code that still works That still solves
the problem. You could have code that
has no slop and is very nice but does not
solve the problem. One thing that we really
wanted to know was what is this interaction
between these two metrics what should we expect
from it? So we basically built
metrics for SLOP. I won't give
a precise definition here. But a lot of what
we've built is basically inspired from old
old constructs from software development.
Things like cyclomatic complexity. But basically,
we've defined sort of two notions of swap.
One is a bit more harmful. The one on the left here
is structural erosion. This basically
says that you're not really doing the right
thing. So the slop has really produced some
kind of fundamentally more bad outcomes
here. You have some very complex code
that isn't really doing the things you'd expect.
And then we have sort of more surface level slop
that's a little bit more benign on the right.
Annoying, for example, if you have totally redundant
functions. Like, could potentially be dangerous.
But it's not quite as bad as what you see on the left.
Now the piece that's interesting here, and I've
failed to label it, but blue is the code agent
orange is a human software developer.
If you kind of check out what happens over time,
starting from the beginning, and then running through a
bunch of checkpoints toward the end of this multi
checkpoint process, humans
really do not sort of increase
their swap levels. Whatever they
started with, they kind of maintain
pretty close to it over time. But
agents do, unfortunately. And in fact, on
on both of these different measurements, of
SLOP, we're actually seeing increases
in erosion and also verbosity.
And of course, agents are actually doing much worse than
humans are right off the bat, but they get even worse
further on. So there's something interesting going
on here. We've been using this benchmark to
develop a lot of different insights and findings.
Seeing some examples here on a couple of models that
we've been testing. You can, of course,
modify the standard
native harnesses for these agents to
incorporate things like anti slot
mechanisms which actually indeed can kind of improve
the slot levels. You're seeing that in this red curve
here. But might be more expensive
and maybe potentially could hurt you
with your pass rate. So we're seeing these kind of
interesting trade offs based on these
paired metrics that we have.
You can check out the newest version. So this
is an interesting example that you're seeing here.
We have sort of two bars over there. So the orange
bar says you get all the checkpoints correct.
The blue bar says although you don't necessarily
get all checkpoints correct, you get
each one in isolation right. At
every checkpoint using only the test for
that checkpoint, you get them right. Even if
you've caused regressions in the past. So orange, of
course, is much harder than blue. It's actually
a subset of it. What we're finding is that
GPD 5.5, when we ran this a couple of
days ago, is actually pretty good. So it's
getting to 65%, if you
only look in isolation at each checkpoint.
Something like about 30% overall.
But this is kind of getting at that difficulty question
We still have a long way to go before we
get close to 90, a 100%
And as you can see on the right, we actually have pretty
high numbers still for all of these on
both measurements. SLOP.
So we have much more on this, and this is all
led by my student, Gabe Orlansky. So all
credit to him for building and carrying forward
this project. He has some really nice
blog posts of insights. Basically, each time
there's a new model release, helped us
sit out and try to look at really what's changed
over time. So for example for
Opus 4.6 and for GPT
5.3 codex, actually
quite interesting that their performance got better, but swap
levels did not improve at all. It was still a sloppy
as ever. 5.4, interestingly,
actually got better at clean code.
And slop reduction but did not really improve performance
wise. There's some really interesting trade
offs happening with each of these model releases.
This is something we're excited about. I encourage everybody
if you're interested to check this out.
So kind of returning to this initial sort
of breakdown of what makes benchmarks
interesting and good, How does
SC Bench really fit these axes? Right? So
for example, for environment, complexity,
you know, we have these agents and multi checkpoint
systems and there's changing requirements. So there's
a lot more complexity than a typical single
shot benchmark. The autonomy
horizon here is certainly nontrivial. It's
not a huge number of steps, but it's more than one
in a way that really challenges our agents.
And we have the usual output complexity of the fact
that you're producing code artifacts that
have a lot of different things that you can go measure.
Alright. So I'm gonna actually stop there, but I do
want to kind of plug our benchmark
program. So for anyone who's interested in
applying, please check it out. We'd love
to work with you. We'd love to hear your cool ideas
for what are gonna be the next set of benchmarks.
Thanks so much everyone for attending and also again for
the organizers.
Thanks a lot, Thrive, for the nice
talk. Do we have do we have question
from the audience? Please come to the microphone.
Maybe let me ask one to get people
started. The warm up question is Sure.
Like, what do you think are
the principles for curating
training data and curating benchmark? What
are the similarities? What are the, like,
differences? What are the most important consideration
here? Think it's an interesting question. There's definitely
some, like, common base that you need. So
quality is always gonna be there. I do think
that training data is usually gonna
bit more idiosyncratic. Right? Like, there are very
weird aspects of data that you wanna
incorporate for training that don't really make sense for
eval. Right? Eval is really gonna track
much more of the way we conceive of data in
the real world. For training, you're gonna have
some differences because fundamentally models
are very different than humans. So I think there's
gonna be some sort of common base and
then some distinctions that you have built on top of
them that are unique to each
I've heard people say that every
benchmark we created in one or two
years, the model will crash it.
Guess that's because the similarity
part, the core part Exactly. Fundamental part
for training and benchmark creation.
There are something there. I think the real
test there is something like can we create a
benchmark today, not release it for
three years? And see what happens afterwards. Right?
I think that would be an interesting experiment, but there's no
incentive for anyone to go do put the time
capsule in. I
think some, like, companies now
create internal
non public private benchmark
But I guess the issue is, like, this
can also be gaming, like, you submit
several times, then you can somewhat
guess how the Exactly. Yeah.
Yeah. I think nothing is truly private ultimately
in the sense.
Do we have more questions?
Thank you very much for your introduction. Can
you say a few words about
this, benchmark
crunch scheme you have? And what are the conditions? What
are you offering? What are you looking for in terms
of domains, in terms of applications? Absolutely.
Yeah. So we are basically open
to a very wide
type of benchmark.
Let me put the point of changing the field and
sort of inspiring the next set of approaches,
whether that's for models or for agents or for systems as a whole.
We're open to all of that. We will
provide resources to kind of help researcher
build these benchmarks. So for example,
if what's necessary is compute, we can help with
that. If what's necessary is sort of
human experts to go craft the
data, we can help with those resources. If what's
necessary really is, you know, a bunch of fellow researchers
to chat with and help build it out, We'll
also kind of do that kind of work. So we provide this kind of
diversity of resources. But, yeah,
we love crazy ideas, so please apply.
So let's thank our speaker again.
Next, we will have a short
sponsored talk
Let's hear more about snorkel.
Listen, now you're here. Yeah.
Okay. It's all yours.
Awesome. Thank you, Fred. And good
to see you all this afternoon. My name is Vincent.
I'm on the founding team at Snorkel,
and one of the research fellows, researchers
there. I get the good pleasure of working
with, Fred. And I just wanted to talk
a little bit about beyond our benchmarking
efforts. What do we what do we do? What are the kind of
techniques and data research we we focus
on? And and why we're really excited to be
you know, here with you all, but also, kind of
pushing the field forward
on the in the
space of data centric AI.
So our overall mission at Snorkel is
to, at a high level, safely
define and advance the frontier with expert
data development. We have a notion
that the future is is going to be one where
humans and AI are are, collaborating in
conjunction, and that frontier
needs to, critically be defined with
experts in the loop. Right? Whether it's
steering or nudging the models in some way, for
automated methods or you
know, providing quality control and, actually
validating the trajectories of some of these
agents. We think that experts are gonna be
really critical for this process. And this is
really the foundation for a lot of
our research is, hey, how do you actually,
steer these models, align these models, program
these models, from a data centric lens with
again, experts, at the home.
So we've been working on this problem
for quite a while. The snorkel project itself
started in 2014 at a, Chris
Ray's group You know,
Our CEO, Alex, is is affiliate at
U Dub. And what's what's unique about our approach
is, we we have the privilege of not just
working in academia, but also
in a number of different venues,
in enterprises, and also,
with Frontier Labs. So a
lot of our focus is actually on bridging
a lot of the the learnings between, all
of these kind of surfaces that we get to touch
and and work with. We work on open research
and bench marks, as Fred mentioned, on
the academic side. We work with Frontier
Labs to help develop their
leading data sets and environments. And
we actually work with enterprises, right? Think Fortune
50, Fortune 100 companies to
build end to end agentic or AI systems
that are actually going to work in in production.
The underlying thread through all of this is that we take
a data centric lens so we're
working on evaluations, we're working on where experts
should be in the loop, and that's really
our focus, is is, you know, taking that
research perspective to serve
all sorts of initiatives both academically with
Frontier Labs and our enterprise customers.
So one of the big changes we've
seen in the past few years really
as the the data stack has moved from
basic generation to
an expert agentic regime is
really an increase in complexity and and domain
expertise needed to steer,
evaluate, and and align these models.
Right. Probably not that long ago, right, just a few years
ago, we were in the basic generation regime
where you know, providing basic instruction
tuning data, right, prompts, responses,
basic preference labels, you know, thumbs up, thumbs
down, was actually sufficient to steering
and evaluating you know, the
the frontier of model capabilities at the time.
And really just, you know, the order of what, twenty four,
thirty six months, we've moved to what we
call, the we call
this the kind of expert agentic regime.
Where there's a lot more complexity and there's a lot more
expertise needed to actually
you know, evaluate and and train these
models. For instance, we're
providing not just kind of basic prompts and
responses now, but defining
tasks with very long horizon
traces, with nuance and complex
outputs. To annotate those
tasks, right, we need rubrics to understand,
hey, is this actually well posed?
Are these actually kind of reasonable,
real world, tasks that you might see in
the field? We're providing step level
preferences and eval labels, and
now defining you know, verifiable outcomes,
at the end of these loops to
identify, hey, how do we actually provide rewards over
these systems? And underlying all of
this are increasingly complex and domain
specific environments. So capturing
a lot of the axes that Fred actually talked about,
right, rich domain specific
context simulated personas,
simulated data in some cases, right, and and,
you know, corpuses that represent
real world settings and tools that are representative
of of you know, actual workloads
in the field, these are what we end up building.
And and a lot of our research and kinda core platform
is focused on supporting
this plethora of complexity and and domain
specific data and environments.
So wanted to also highlight four of the
ways that we think the field is going, four of
the ways that we think you know,
we have been investing in our core
to drive the frontier
of of data centric systems.
First, as I mentioned earlier, we believe that these
specialized AI agented systems need to be
driven by Right? Increasingly, the value
is gonna be coming in domains where
you need a clinician, you need an underwriter,
need an analyst to actually help you
define both what good looks like and two,
how to steer these models, in practice.
Two, excuse me,
quality matters more than ever. This
is a regime where you're not, you
know, crowdsourcing millions and millions
of labels, you know, with multiple replications.
Right? These are settings where every
ounce of quality matters for the end outcome.
And as a result, the data that you use,
the environments that you use to train these systems and
and and models need to be extremely
high quality. So a lot of our research goes
into how we actually improve that quality control
life cycle, everything from the
theoretical foundations built on
a lot of our weak supervision work from years ago
to some of the HCI and systems level
considerations. Diversity
matters as well, right, in order to build systems that
actually match real world tasks,
you need data environment and environments
that capture the long tail of,
these real workloads. And three,
we need a headroom. We need to, avoid model
saturation and represent real
frontier complexity as I talked about on the previous slide.
So a few ways that we're doing this, in our research
and systems one, we we
have a really strong, human data network,
right, of thousand expert
level topics covering everything from stem
to, commercial and and industry domains
to domains like tourism, retail,
fitness. A big part
of our our internal company is focused
on, hey, building and and and recruiting
and and retaining these experts and also pairing
them with you know, researchers like Fred and
myself and and a lot of the engineers on our end
to ensure that they're building
these data sets in environments with the latest
frontier research considerations in mind.
Two, we invest a lot in
programmatic quality control and feedback
loops to deliver the highest quality data.
This loop that I have here was actually taken
from one of our workflows for for one of our
front tier projects. It's actually simplified,
believe it or not. And a lot of the
idea here is really to build these frontier
types of data sets, you often need
novel quality control mechanisms. In this case,
this actually resembles a bit of an
academic peer review type system. And and for all
of its faults, we're all
here today, but, there's a lot of good learnings
for how we can actually take expert
level review processes, judgments, you know, rebuttal
systems, to steer the future
of, data points in domains like theoretical
physics, or medicine where, you
know, every an individual person in
this room might not actually be able to assess or adjudicate,
hey, is this actually a high quality
data point or task? You actually need that
peer review to assess quality at the frontier.
So Another thing we focus a lot on is,
diversity or or kind of fine fine grained
distributional control. In order
to match the distribution of real world tasks
as I mentioned, there's a number of systems
and workflows we need to build internally in order
to propagate both kind
of volume and and diversity across
these types of you know, search spaces.
And so a lot of our research again is focused
on systems that help us control
that, diversity, volume,
trade off. In order to
get more coverage scale and and
coverage failure mode exploration.
And lastly, I wanna emphasize emphasize, you know, this is a really
iterative loop. You know, we've been working on
this process with
our platform for over a decade now.
Around, you know, hey, how do you really quickly build evaluators
really quickly? And ingest expert
signal into your your evaluators
and inquire
and into your systems with with
really high velocity. And this is something that
powers a lot of kind of rapid
quality control, rapid iteration that we we pride
ourselves on. And so a lot of our research also focus
iteration loop, which again, helps
us, you know,
So levels of complexity
and difficulty, and and new domains.
And so as Fred mentioned, you know, a lot of what
we're excited about
are new agentic environments that focus
on some of these three axes. That that Fred
talked about briefly. Autonomy horizon,
how independently can these agents operate,
in long horizon tasks? Right, going
from minutes to hours
to weeks to months, in terms of the the
level of autonomy that we provide to these
agents. And also critically,
considering different points on the autonomy slider.
Right? So where do you actually want a human to be in the
loop How much do you want a human to be involved
in these systems?
These are research questions that we're really excited
about, both kind of building internally, but also
funding via the open benchmarks grants.
Is environment complexity. A lot of what I just
alluded to refers to the fact
that we need more dynamic, more realistic
environments that represent real use cases
that you see in the wild. Right? So we
work with our enterprise customers, right, in finance
and medicine and insurance to
help them solve these problems at the frontier,
generating more and more of these types
of environments is increasingly the bottleneck that
we see in these, frontier cases
where, again, every point, every subpoint
of of accuracy matters?
And lastly, output complexity is something we're
really interested in. Right? We're we're moving
way past this regime of simple
text in, text out type of systems.
You're getting as outputs, you know, complex strategy
reports or, you know, entire slide decks
and evaluating quality in these settings
is nontrivial. So
actually capturing the increased sophistication
of these output types and
measuring and and post training against these is,
increasingly important in one of our key, research
areas. So I just
wanted to stop in and and share some of those notes
on some of the research we're focused on. If
this is interesting at all,
please reach out. Apply to one of our open
benchmarks grants as Fred
mentioned earlier. And, we're really excited we'll be around
today, and know, at the booth and otherwise,
and excited to chat further about,
all of, your your recent and data
centric AI directions. Thanks so much for
having us.
Thanks, Vincent, for giving the talk and
thanks Norco for the generous
sponsorship for of the workshop.
They are supposed to be here, and we have a lot
of snorkel people in the room. Feel
free to talk with them. Offline
and, yeah. So
I think we still have
the poster session. We still have time. We can
stay until five. But
I'm talking as a
conclude concluding or
closing remark to our online
audience and for the future audience,
So I think this wraps up all
our talks today. It's
a really exciting program. Very happy
to have all of you, especially
current people in the room who stayed late.
Like refills the nice sunshine
on the beach at Rio here.
And we hear a lot of research
progress, interesting
talks, and a lot of good posters
here for data research.
And, let's see
Like some people that
may think about data model for engineering rather
than research. I hope this workshop
shows that it's not. It's
a lot of research and it's a really
important research we have to do.
And last year, I organized
a different workshop on
dedicated to synthetic data.
But now this year, we merged it into
this workshop And as you can see
from what the talks and all the discussions,
sensitive data is already everywhere,
like it's used everywhere.
And when we proposed this workshop, we
have something like we keep seeing
new needs and the new research directions
for data. Like multimodal
and IR and all that. But
when we come here at this
at this workshop, like, after six months,
we hear even more. Like, all
these agents, reasoning, really
interesting study.
So hopefully, like, we will see
more of the research in data
next time. Thanks to our
sponsors, Norco and, Datalogree
again. And, hope to see you
all. Next time.
Thank you.